<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY appversion "0.9.b51">
<!ENTITY date "March 2019">
<!ENTITY app "NsCDE">
]>

<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="en"> 
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->
<articleinfo> 
 <title>Not so Common Desktop Environment (&app;) Manual</title>
 <abstract role="description">
    <para>
    This manual describes NsCDE: Not so Common Desktop Environment
    </para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2019</year>
      <holder>M. Z.</holder>
    </copyright>

    <authorgroup> 
      <author>
        <firstname>M. </firstname>
        <surname>Z.</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup> 

    <releaseinfo>
      This manual describes version &appversion; of &app;.
    </releaseinfo> 
</articleinfo> 

<!-- ============= Index ===================================== -->
<indexterm zone="index"> 
<primary>&app;</primary> 
</indexterm>

<!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->
<!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->

<sect1 id="NsCDE-intro"> 
<title>Introduction</title> 

<sect2 id="NsCDE-whatis"> 
<title>What is NsCDE?</title> 

<para>
In a nutshell, NsCDE is the CDE clone. Tehnically, it can be considered a heavy FVWM theme
enriched with additional free software tools and applications, combining all
this components into something which can be called lightweight hybrid
desktop environment. It can even be integrated into existing desktop
environments as a window manager wrapper for session handling and
additional DE functionality.
</para>

<para>
NsCDE's main goal is to revive look and feel of the Common Desktop
Environment found on many UNIX and unix-like systems during nineties and first
decade of the 21 century, but with a slightly polished interface (XFT,
unicode, dynamic changes, rich key and mouse bindings, desk pages,
rich menus etc) and a goal to produce comfortable "retro" environment
which is not just a eye candy toy, but a real working environment for
users who contrary to mainstream trends really like CDE, thus making semi-optimal
blend of usability and compatibility with modern tools with look and feel which mainstream
abadoned for some new fashion, and ... in a nutshell, giving to user the best of the both worlds.
</para>

<para>
Main driver behind NsCDE is the excellent FVWM window manager with it's
endless options for customization, GUI Script engine, Colorsets, and modules.
NsCDE is largely a wrapper around FVWM - something like a heavyweight theme,
sort of.
</para>

<para>
Other main components are GTK2, GTK3, Qt4 and Qt5 theme for unifying look and feel
for the most Unix/Linux applications, custom scripts which are helpers and
backend workers for GUI parts and some data from the original CDE, as icons,
palettes, and backdrops.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-why"> 
<title>Why NsCDE?</title>

<para>
Since the 90-ties, I have always liked this environment and it's somewhat crude
socrealistic look in a contrast to "modern" Windows and GNOME approach which is going in
the opposite taste from what I always liked to see on my screen. I have
created this environment for my own usage 8-10 years ago and it was a
patchwork, chaotic and not well suited for sharing with someone. While it
looked ok on the surface, behind it was a years of ad hoc hacks and senseless
configurations and scripts, dysfunctional menus etc. Couple of months in a row
I had a time and chance to rewrite this as a more consistent environment,
first for myself, and during this process, idea came to do it even better, and
put on the web for everyone else who may like this idea of modern CDE.
</para>

<para>
NsCDE is intended for a people which doesn't like "modern" hypes, interfaces
that try to mimic Mac and Windows and reimplementing their ideas for
non-technical user's desktops, and reimplementing them poorly. Older and mature
system administrators, programmers and generally people from the Unix
background are more likely to have attraction to NsCDE. It is probably not well suited for
beginners.
</para>

<para>
Of course, question arises: why not simply use original original CDE now when it is open sourced?
</para>

<para>
Apart from desirable look, because it has it's own problems: it is a product
from 90-ties, based on Motif and time has passed since then. In CDE there is
no really XFT font rendering, no immediate application dynamic changes. Beside
that, I have found dtwm, CDE's window manager inferior to FVWM and some 3rd party solutions which
can be paired with it. So I wanted the best of the two worlds: good old retro
look and feel from original CDE, but more flexible, modern and maintained
"driver" behind it, which will allow for individual customizations as one
find's them fit for it's own amusement and usage. As it will be seen later,
there are some intentional differences between CDE and NsCDE - a middle line
between trying to stay as close as possible to look of the CDE, but with more
flexibility and functionality on the second and third look.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-components">
<title>Components of the NsCDE</title>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-components-overview">
<title>Components overview</title>
<para>
NsCDE is a wrapper and a bunch of configurations, scripts and apps around
FVWM. FVWM is in my opinion a model of free choice for people who like to have
things set up by their own wishes and who are aware what real freedom of
choice is. A stunning contrast to policies forced on Linux users in the last
decade from the mainstream desktop players.
</para>

<para>
NsCDE is by default rooted in <filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE</filename> ($NSCDE_ROOT),
but it can be relocated with only one variable changed in main
wrapper <filename class="directory">bin/nscde</filename> and <filename>NsCDE-Main.conf</filename>.
</para>

<para>
It is not using your existing <filename class="directory">$HOME/.fvwm</filename>
but sets <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> to <filename class="directory">$HOME/.NsCDE</filename>,
and uses <filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE/config</filename> as a sources of configuration.
</para>

<para>
Configuration model is a bit complex, but very flexible: configuration options
are grouped in logical order. Configuration files are names
<filename>NsCDE-&lt;group&gt;.conf</filename>. For example, <filename>NsCDE-Functions.conf</filename>
for FVWM functions. Each
configuration file can have two exclusive sources, and one additional. For
example, if user doesn't have <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Functions.conf</filename>, then
<filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/NsCDE-Functions.conf</filename> is read as default. Additionally, if
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Functions.local</filename> exists, it will be read in addition to
conf file, from wherever it was read. This is intended as a primary mechanism
for customization: If user doesn't need to override and change a lot of
"system" configuration, but just add it's own in addition to existing, local
file is place for such customization (of course, most parts of the existing FVWM
configuration can be overridden or destroyed and recreated even in local files.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-components-applets-tools">
<title>Applets and GUI Tools</title>
<para>
NsCDE provides GUI tools which are built in FvwmScript(1) and their shell and
python helpers. Also, some external applications that fit in the picture as
recommended. This tools are mainly built by me, but some, such as mouse,
keyboard and beep control are modified from the default FVWM scripts to look
more CDEish and they implement some additional functionality.
</para>

<para>
Applets docks and panels are:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Front Panel (FvwmButtons)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Subpanels (FvwmButtons)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Workspace Manager (WSM) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Page Manager (PGM) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>MonthDayApplet - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Clock - External C applet pclock</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>CheckMailApplet - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>FpLite - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
GUI tools are:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Style Manager (StlyeMgr) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Backdrop Style Manager (BackdropMgr) - FvwmScript + Korn Shell</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Beep Style Manager - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Color Style Manager (ColorMgr) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ExecDialog - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Font Style Manager (FontMgr) - FvwmScript + Korn Shell</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Keyboard Style Manager (KeyboardMgr) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Occupy Workspace (OccupyWorkspace) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mouse Style Manager (PointerMgr) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Power Save Manager (PowerSaveMgr) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Subpanel Manager (SubpanelMgr) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Subpanel Settings (SubpanelSettings) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>System Action Dialog (SysActionDialog) - FvwmScript, sudo</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sysinfo - FvwmScript, python</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Window Style Manager (WindowMgr) - FvwmScript, sed, egrep</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Workspaces and Pages Manager (WsPgMgr) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

<para>
Helper Dialogs:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>ActionForm - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ChoiceForm - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>FilePicker - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>InputForm - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>WaitNotice - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NColorsDialog (<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> part) -
 FvwmScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>PaletteDialog - (Backdrop Style Manager part) - FvwmScript</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
External fit-in Programs:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Xscreensaver (xscreensaver-demo called from StyleMgr) installed separately.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-applets-docks-panels">
<title>Applets Docks and Panels</title>
<sect2 id="NsCDE-FrontPanel">
<title>Front Panel</title>
<para>
In NsCDE, CDE Front Panel is mimicked and re-implemented with the help of FvwmButtons(1)
Configuration is done under alias <emphasis>*FrontPanel</emphasis> in
<filename>NsCDE-FrontPanel.conf</filename>,
read and activated from the <filename>NsCDE-Main.conf</filename>.
Visually, this is remake almost in a pixel as CDE Front Panel. The main
differences are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
   Icons are static in configuration. FvwmButtons doesn't implement drag
     and drop protocol. It can be changed and customized in a two ways:
     first one, 8 of 10 icons (minus swallowed applets clock, calendar and mail
     that is) can be dinamically changed by writing button actions and icon paths
     in <filename>FrontPanel.actions</filename> in user's <filename class="directory">
     $FVWM_USERDIR</filename> and this will be applied <emphasis>after</emphasis>
     reading static configuration and running Front Panel for a piece of a second.
     The other way (full control) is by copying configuration file from
     <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/config</filename> to
     <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   In the original CDE, Front Panel is part of the dtwm Window Manager
     binary, while here it is configuration of FvwmButtons(1) FVWM module. Workspace
     Manager in the middle of the Front Panel is a separate applet written
     in FvwmScript(1).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   On every icon, for all 3 main mouse buttons different action can be
     assigned. This is used for example 8th icon where mouse button 1
     calls editor, while mouse button 3 is calling file manager (if defined)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   In addition to iconification, Front Panel can be shaded to the bottom
     edge of the screen with <keysym>Shift-Esc</keysym> action, and put
     in a place with the same shortcut again.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Iconification is by default to bottom right screen edge, while all other
     programs are by default iconified in the top left edge as in CDE.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   It is flexible, can be overlapped with programs, moves away for fully
     maximized windows and while pretty much thick, not in the way while not
     needed.
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
   - It has it's own menu on top left button and special context menu if this
     button is clicked with right mouse button. Middle mouse button behaves as
     if title bar is clicked - with special diagnostic tool menu.
     Right-clicked special menu has this important tasks:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Calls Workspace and Page Manager Manager</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Restart WorkSpace Manager</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Restart Page Manager</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Restart Panel Clock (pclock)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Restart Panel Mail Applet</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Restart Panel Date (MonthDayApplet)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Restart Panel Lite (FpLite)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Restart the whole Front Panel</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
As FvwmButtons based dock, it swallows the following applets:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>pclock (external standalone app with CDEish skin)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>MonthDayApplet (FvwmScript)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>CheckMailApplet (FvwmScript)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>PGM (FvwmScript)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>WSM / Workspace Manager (FvwmScript)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>FpLite (FvwmScript)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Third icon expects <varname>$[infostore.filemgr]</varname> to be defined.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Fourth icon will call <varname>$[infostore.terminal]</varname> which
   must be defined or it is discovered.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Sixth or Print icon is not really usable. It should call some predefined
   printer application in the future or to be replaced with something more
   useful. Good place for personal custom icon and redefinition with
   <filename>FrontPanel.actions</filename>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Seventh: <link linkend="NsCDE-StyleMgr">Style Manager</link> - clone of the well
   known CDE Launcher of "Style" tools.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <varname>$[infostore.xeditor]</varname> - if defined in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE.conf.</filename>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Semi-empty. By default, it popups 9th subpanel if pressed. A nice idea is
   to call pavucontrol or some audio mixer on 3rd mouse click from <filename>FrontPanel.actions</filename>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Help, documentation.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   Front Panel Subpanels 2, 5 and 6 are empty, but they can be activated with
   middle pointer click on an empty place. Dialog will ask user if he wants it
   enabled. This is specially useful for subpanel 5 which will show
   Thunderbird if activated and if Thunderbird is installed.
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
   Subpanel 1: Applications
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Subpanel 3: Libre Office Components and various office/productivity tools
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Subpanel 4: System Tools
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Subpanel 7: NsCDE Style Manager and various Qt, Gtk and misc management applications
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Subpanel 8: Tools
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Subpanel 9: Multimedia programs: audio, video, photo ...
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Subpanel 10: Documentation
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   In the center of the Front Panel there is a place without subpanel
   launchers and separated by vertical line. Inside this area, there are
   4 small command icons: Left: Lock Screen (<command>xscreensaver -activate</command>), Page Manager (PGM),
   Right are Front Panel Lite (system load indicator), and <guibutton>Exit</guibutton> button
   (SysActionDialog).
</para>
<para>
   In the middle of this area there is WSM - Work Space Manager with well
   known four buttons for four virtual desks. By default, four desks are
   shown and configured, but this can be changed
   (see <xref linkend="NsCDE-Workspace-Manager"/>).
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Subpanels">
<title>Subpanels</title>

<para>
NsCDE subpanels are simple transient FvwmButton docks. As Front Panel, they
are also as much as possible similar to original CDE forms of the same
purpose. Some applications in them are predefined, and discovered if
installed, and the rest is up to user to populate.
Their purpose is not to show all possible GUI applications installed on the
system as right-click root menu. They are meant for favorite, important and often
used apps.
</para>
<para>
There is one main difference between CDE and NsCDE subpanels: <emphasis>Install Icon</emphasis>
action calls special NsCDE tool for actions defining. There is no drag and
drop from the app manager (which also doesn't exist).
</para>
<para>
Each Subpanel's application item or entry has additional third mouse pointer button action which
will pop up dinamically populated contextual menu named after item's title. Here, there are actions
to move up or down item for one space on the subpanel, to move item to the beginning or the end of
the subpanel's application list, as well as to delete item from the subpanel (warning message will
appear before deletion is really performed). First menu item is the same as menu name: title of
the application from submenu. If clicked, it will perform default action as if item's title or icon
was clicked on the submenu itself. This is a kind of a escape from the contextual menu, but to
still use subpanel's default action without repeating opening of a submenu again.
If move or delete action is silently not performed, this is most likely the situation where
user's <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Subpanels.actions</filename> is newer than
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Subpanels.conf</filename>, and must be rebuilt for configuration
actions to take a place properly. In that case, repeated operation must succeed, otherwise,
see X session error log for details.
</para>
<para>
Subpanels, like in CDE has titlebars but as windows on screen they are without
borders and handles. They have only left menu button like other windows, but
with one exception: there are no actions for closing window and re-positioning
it (no sense in this), but they have "Refresh Subpanel" and "Subpanel
Settings" controls. First one kills process module, re-reads it's
configuration and starts it on the next click on Front Panel subpanel
launcher. Subpanel Settings is the small and simple FvwmScript tool which
allows one to rename Subpanel, set it's width for application titles to fit if
necessary, and to enable or disable that particular Subpanel.
</para>

<para>
On the first change with <emphasis>Install Icon</emphasis> or <emphasis>Subpanel Settings</emphasis>,
non-FVWM configuration file <emphasis>Subpanels.actions</emphasis> will be created in the
<varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>, from where all subpanels changed from default will be read
by the <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/generate_subpanels</command>, while the rest will be
generated from the <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Subpanels.actions</filename>. This file can also
be edited by hand (ok, not by hand, but editor will suffice) and the result may be applied by
calling <command>generate_subpanels</command> and then <function>f_ReadCfg Subpanels</function>.
Generated file is called <filename>NsCDE-Subpanels.conf</filename> and it is expected in the
<varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>. If not found there,
<filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/NsCDE-Subpanels.conf</filename> will be read instead.
Syntax of the Subpanels.actions is explained in the
<link linkend="NsCDE-Configuration-Files">Configuration files explained</link> section.
</para>

<para>
Presently, there is one workaround here: as much as FVWM, and specially FvwmButtons are
very flexible and configurable, no title for the buttons app can be set apart
from module alias, but module alias doesn't support names with spaces in them.
Internal names as <emphasis>"NsCDE-SubpanelX"</emphasis> are for that reason referenced in
<filename>NsCDE-FrontPanel.conf</filename>, and are internally mandatory names of their Subpanels.
Since there is no configuration option for subpanel to set Window Title, we are using here
tool <command>xdotool(1)</command> which is run on Subpanel initialization with a delay of 3,2
seconds (internal workaround for xdotool) and this then takes infostore
variable <varname>NsCDE-SubpanelX-Name</varname> and sets literal, system default or user picked
name of the subpanel. Presently, an alternative option is to apply FvwmButtons patch which introduces a
<emphasis>WindowName</emphasis> option to it's configuration. Of course, patch will be proposed
to the upstream FVWM.
</para>
<para>
The rest about Subpanel, or to say their visible outfit, and their main function
are the same as in CDE - a nice, heavyweight and elegant application launchers.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Workspace-Manager">
<title>Workspace Manager</title>
<para>
Workspace Manager is a Widget in the center of the Front Panel. Visually, it
replicates in almost a pixel similarity with the center of the CDE's Workspace
Manager's buttons, but with a few exceptions beneath the surface and further
configuration:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 There is a limited number for possible of desks. There can be no odd number of
  desks, and combinations are: 2, 4, 6 and 8. Default is of course 4.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Buttons are not fixed in width size as in CDE. They are not extending a
  width of the Front Panel, rather they are more wide in 2-buttons
  combination, and narrow in 6 and 8 button combination.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 As in CDE, desk names can be renamed. There is a keyboard combination in
  FvwmScript WSM which enters rename mode: Ctrl+Space on the current active
  desk, while pointer is inside WSM. <keysym>Ctrl+Enter</keysym> saves new name. Names are
  synchronized with FVWM desktop names and used in the rest of the
  configuration. Names are saved in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/WSM.conf</filename>
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Addition: right mouse button on desk button brings contextual menu. From
  this menu, global (all desks and their pages), or local (pages of the one
  desk) FvwmPager - visual pager can be called. Below this menu options, there
  is an option to bring up Window List, and small submenu for changing the active page
  on the current desk.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 If <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/WSM.conf</filename> value <emphasis>WSPPG</emphasis> is 1,
  then in 2 or 4 desks/buttons
  mode a small current page indicator is show on the right side of the button.
  In addition to Page Manager (PGM) southwest of the WSM. Disabled (0) by default.
  <filename>WSM.conf</filename> (system wide: <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/WSM.conf</filename>) is
  a separate configuration
  file read by WSM, PGM, WsPgMgr and such. Not a FVWM configuration file.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Number of Desks and Pages can be configured with Workspace and Page Manager
  tool which is called with right pointer click on Front Panel's left button
  and selected from the menu.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
State of the buttons is synchronized by FVWM function called from FvwmEvent(1)
module whenever desks and pages are changed by other means, such as keyboard
shortcut, mouse move, or <command>FvwmCommand(1)</command>.
</para>

<para>
In 4 color palette mode, all WSM buttons are of the same color, while in 8 colors
mode, there are four color variations from the given palette.
</para>

<para>
Desks in NsCDE are named and numbered from 1, while in FVWM, they start from
0. This fact required additional effort while coding FvwmScripts and making
default and core configuration.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-PGM">
<title>Page Manager</title>
<para>
Page Manager is entirely new thing.
There is no concept of <emphasis>Pages</emphasis> in the original CDE,
just desks (workspaces). This nice feature of pages is too useful to be disabled
and sacrificed just to get even more CDE similarity, but really zealous user can configure NsCDE not
to include pages, just desks. PGM is a small FvwmScript applet
southwest from the WSM, represented by the silver-gray icon of the desk
divided on <emphasis>pagesX</emphasis> x <emphasis>pagesY</emphasis>.
Default is 2x2, that is, four pages per every
desk, which in default first run gives 4 x 4 = 16 screens for applications.
Minimum for pages is 0, and maximum 16. For example, in maximal desks+pages
configuration, one gets 8x16 desktop, that is 128 screens! While undoubtedly
this is diversion from a more flexible plain FVWM configuration, it covers
really great number of possible preferences. Pages can be configured in any
<emphasis>XxY</emphasis> combination. For example 1x4, 2x3, 3x3, 2x1, 2x2 ...
</para>
<para>
PGM changes icon to represent position of the current page on
current desk while user moves from page to page automatically with the help of
the FvwmEvent(1) just like the WSM.
</para>
<para>
When clicked, PGM transforms in a closed popup menu with names of the
pages and special "..." option on the top which calls local visual FvwmPager.
When option from the menu is selected, menu again transforms to the Icon. If
called, but not clicked, menu automatically transforms back into Icon after 20
seconds of inactivity. Middle pointer button calls Workspace and Page Manager,
while the right pointer button calls visual Local Pager.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-MonthDayApplet">
<title>MonthDayApplet</title>
<para>
Usual CDE icon with month and day of the month in it. Simple applet which
calls empty, do-nothing (by default) function <function>f_Calendar</function>. This function can be
overridden in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Functions.local</filename> to call a program which user
wishes.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Pclock">
<title>Front Panel Clock - pclock</title>
<para>
This is a small C program (GPL) written many years ago by Alexander Kourakos.
It supports XPM skins and displays hours, minutes and seconds. It is well
suited for window manager docks like FvwmButtons(1). In NsCDE it is applied with
a skin similar to original one, but slightly bigger and with more clear edges
and colors. Default can be used from
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/icons/CDE</filename> or even
replaced with a Solaris version with picture of the globe with red hands for
hours and minutes and white for seconds. If clicked, it will try to execute
firefox by default (which appears doesn't work if FVWM is started under some
desktop environment like MATE).
Pclock C source is provided for user's convenience if it
needs to be recompiled on another system or architecture. Source is in
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/src/pclock-0.13.1</filename>.
With NsCDE binary for Linux is provided by
default in <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/bin</filename>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-CheckMailApplet">
<title>Check Mail Applet</title>
<para>
Fifth icon from the left on Front Panel is FvwmScript applet. It is calling
<function>f_CheckMail</function> FVWM function every minute. If clicked, function is called immediately.
By default <function>f_CheckMail</function> is an empty function. Up to user is to redefine it in his
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Functions.local</filename> to suit the needs for mail checking. To be
clear, by default, it is not functional as an applet. Above this applet, there
is an empty space for subpanel launcher which can be activated with middle
click, and it will present Thunderbird entry if thunderbird is installed. User
can use <emphasis>Install Icon</emphasis> action to change or add entries on this menu. For
example, to call <command>urxvt -e</command> mutt or something like that.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-FpLite">
<title>FpLite</title>
<para>
Load Indicator on the top right side of the center of the Front Panel contains
a small applet called FpLite. In original CDE it was used to indicate desktop
activity, but since on today's processors this tasks are short and almost
immediate (specially with a good window manager such as FVWM), I find it
better suited to show system load. It has 10 micro-bars. When there is no
load, all are yellow. Load grows from left to right. First 5 green bars, then
3 blue, 2 magenta, an after that it starts from the beginning with red bars.
FpLite summarizes load of all CPUs on the system in a way that 1-minute load
is divided with number of CPU cores, and then counted as such while displaying
load with color micro-bars. Everything under 1 (internally 100) is yellow,
green, blue and magenta, and after that it counts 10 red micro-bars. For
example: on the system with 2 CPU cores, 1-minute load of 0.6 will be
presented with 3 bars (0.6 / num-cores), load of 2.2 will be presented with
one red bar etc ... on the system with four CPU cores load of 3 will be
magenta on the two rightmost bars, and load of 4 or more will be red. Load of
more than (numcpu * 10) will not be shown specially, but user gets an idea
what is going on if FpLite is all red.
If clicked, it will call a function <function>f_FpLiteClickAction</function> which is by default
set to safe defaults (<emphasis>[default terminal app]</emphasis> <command>-e top</command>).
FpLite FvwmScript app uses little portable python script <emphasis>getla1.py</emphasis> from the
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec</filename> to obtain 1-minute load data.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-GUI-Tools">
<title>GUI Tools</title>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-StyleMgr">
<title>Style Manager</title>
<para>
This Window is a starting point for all other <emphasis>Style Manager</emphasis> applications to be
called. It is called from 7th button on the Front Panel. It has big icons for
calling:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-FontMgr">Font Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-KeyboardMgr">Keyboard Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-PointerMgr">Mouse Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-BeepMgr">Beep Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Xscreensaver Demo (setup)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="NsCDE-PowerSaveMgr">Power Style Manager</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Startup Style Manager</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
If NsCDE was started under X Session Manager, Startup Style Manager icon will
call setup tool for that session manager or DE. Otherwise, error message is displayed:
either that NsCDE was not started under X Session Management, or X Session
Manager is not recognized, and it's setup tool cannot be run. Currently,
only MATE, LXDE, KDE and GNOME session managers are recognized and their respective
tools called. See <xref linkend="NsCDE-Startup"/> about running NsCDE under X Session Manager for more
information about this matter.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">
<title>Backdrop Style Manager</title>
<para>
Part of the Style Managers which can be called from the main Style Manager (7th button on the Front Panel).
This is the clone of the same-named CDE tool. It loads backdrops from the
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/backdrops</filename> and
<filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/backdrops</filename> (if any). From XPM
backdrop templates with symbol names (with .pm extension) it will generate
previews in user's <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/tmp</filename> and if
applied or <guibutton>OK</guibutton>'ed, will set
permanent backdrop in <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/backer</filename>. Backer is named after
FvwmBacker(1) module which then loads this X Pixmap as numbered FVWM Colorset
from the <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Backdrops.conf</filename> which will be
written by Backdrop Style Manager (or by hand). Backdrops are generated in the colors of the
current color theme from the active palette (<emphasis>Broica</emphasis> by default). It has
different colors for a group of every four desktops in 8-colors mode and the
same base color in 4-color mode. Generated backdrop in the
<filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/backer</filename> are named
<filename>DeskN-&lt;name-of-the-backdrop&gt;.pm</filename> where <emphasis>N</emphasis> is
the workspace (desk) number from 1-8. In such a way it is possible to have the same
backdrop pattern on more than one desk in 8-colors mode.
</para>
<para>
There is an option to use the same backdrop for all desks too.
User can add and delete custom backdrops in <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/backdrops</filename>. 
First action with <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button and file picker, and second action with
<guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button when particular backdrop from the list on the right of the preview is
selected. Delete action will fail for system-pathed backdrops with appropriate
error message, while both actions will reload list of backdrops immediately.
Apart from doing this, NsCDE Backdrop Style Manager has couple of features
more than CDE original:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 In 8-color mode, user can select another color variant instead of default
  for the current desk from the popup menu. There are four variants.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Custom palette can be loaded instead of default one, and backdrops can be
  set with colors from that palette. In 8-colors mode, there is even more
  possibility of course.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Instead of backdrops, user can opt for a background image. If option "Use
  photo or picture is selected, list of backdrops will dissapear and image
  backgrounds (so called "wallpapers") will be loaded from
  <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/photos</filename> and from the
  <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/photos</filename> (if any). Options to
  use one photo for all desks exists. In this mode, backdrop-specific options
  will be hidden until <guilabel>Use photo or picture</guilabel> is not deselected.
  <guibutton>Add</guibutton> and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> of photos/pictures is
  supported in a same way as for backdrops. Photos must be in PNG or XPM format to be loaded.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Backdrop Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>P</keysym>: Applies preview of the currently selected backdrop (or photo) on the root window.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Up/Down</keysym>: Selects previous or next element on the backdrop (or photo) list.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-BeepMgr">
<title>Beep Style Manager</title>
<para>
Simple tool to adjust system beep device - if it is present as device and if desired/enabled.
This tool uses xset(1) <emphasis> b</emphasis> command to set volume, pitch and duration of the beep
sound. Modified setting can be tested with additional <guibutton>Beep</guibutton> button which is not
present in the original tool, and also dynamically applied with <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button.
<guibutton>Save</guibutton> button will save <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xset.conf</filename> with other
xset(1) options which are executed during NsCDE startup.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Beep Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Beep Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-ColorMgr">
<title>Color Style Manager</title>
<para>
With Backdrop Style Manager, this is probably the most important theme tool in (Ns)CDE. This tool
applies colors to the widgets, menus, applications and backdrops. As in CDE,
it reads color information from the palette files in
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/palettes</filename> and
<filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/palettes</filename>. Palettes are the 16bpp
color definitions (8 of them). This colors and border bg/fg/sel colors
calculated from them are the base of the look of pretty much all of the things
on the screen. Colors can be applied in 4 or 8 colors mode. Most notable
palettes are <emphasis>Broica</emphasis> in 8-colors mode and <emphasis>Solaris</emphasis>
(called <emphasis>Default</emphasis> on SunOS) in 4 colors mode.
</para>
<para>
Color Style Manager as most tools is written in FvwmScript with background
shell helper and color calculation and generator routines. Visually it tries
to be as much as possible similar to the original CDE, but since it has some
new features, there are some new buttons and commands introduced.
Tool has a list of the palettes (system + user), preview button which can
temporary apply some palette on the current desk backdrop and FVWM based
applications (FrontPanel, other scripts ...)
</para>
<para>
As in Backdrop Style Manager there are <guibutton>Add</guibutton> and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton>
button actions. System palettes cannot be deleted, while local can be added to
<filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/palettes</filename> and applied immediately.
</para>
<para>
There are 8 spaces with colors from the currently selected palette (4 spaces
in 4-color mode) and generated XPM file with all 40 colors displayed.
Button <guibutton>Number of Colors</guibutton> calls transient window where user can select 4 or 8
color mode. System default on modern desktop is 8.
</para>
<para>
What is most important new feature in Color Style Manager are integration
options. This are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 Own currently used backdrop synchronization (default)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 X resources in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xdefaults</filename> (default)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 GTK2
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 GTK3
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Qt4
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Qt5
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 User's <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/libexec/colormgr.local</filename> script if exists, called with
  the path of the applied palette and number of colors.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The last integration is used to integrate what default widget integrations
cannot reach. For example Gkrellm skin or some terminal preferences.
Qt/Qt5 integration is easy, since this toolkits can use their <emphasis>GTK</emphasis> engine to
integrate self with GTK theme. All that Color Style Manager has to do is to
define GTK engine in <filename>~/.config/Trolltech.conf</filename> and
<filename>~/.config/qt5ct/qt5ct.conf</filename> for colors from the new palette to be used.
</para>
<para>
GTK2 and GTK3 are heavy work part. Here, we are using work derived from one
CDE theme for XFCE desktop and GTK2 + GTK3, purified and adapted for NsCDE
(see <xref linkend="NsCDE-Credits"/>).
This is written in python. If turned on, this will produce
<filename class="directory">$HOME/.themes/NsCDE</filename>
directory with the theme for GTK2 and GTK3, and will edit <filename>$HOME/.gtkrc-2.0</filename> and
<filename>$HOME/.config/gtk-3.0/settings.ini</filename> to put or change
<varname>gtk-theme-name</varname> value.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Color Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>P</keysym>: Like <guibutton>Preview</guibutton> was pressed. Previews currently selected
color scheme from the list.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Up/Down</keysym>: Goes one item on the color schemes list up or down.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-ExecDialog">
<title>Exec Dialog</title>
<para>
By default key binding for Exec Dialog is <keysym>Meta</keysym> (mod4) + <keysym>F2</keysym>,
and located on main root menu before
terminal i a "Exec" dialog. This is an input form for executing one-shot
commands without terminal. It has options to run command in terminal
(<varname>$[infostore.terminal]</varname>), and to remain open after executing commands for
subsequent commands. It has it's own command history which can be turned back
with cursor <keysym>up</keysym> and <keysym>down</keysym> keys. <keysym>Escape</keysym> key
closes dialog, <keysym>enter</keysym> executes, <keysym>Ctrl+Enter</keysym> executes in default
terminal application.
</para>
<para>
As an example, this dialog can be used if on the current page or desk terminal application is
not present, and only some simple command is needed to be quickly executed.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Exec dialog
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Return</keysym>: Performs an action like if <guibutton>Exec</guibutton> is pressed.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Return</keysym>: Performs an action like if <guibutton>Exec</guibutton> is pressed,
and <guilabel>Execute in terminal</guilabel> checkbox is checked.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Shift+Return</keysym>: Performs an action like if <guibutton>Exec</guibutton> is pressed,
and <guilabel>Leave this dialog open</guilabel> checkbox is checked.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Shift+Return</keysym>: Performs an action like if <guibutton>Exec</guibutton> is pressed,
<guilabel>Execute in terminal</guilabel> and <guilabel>Leave this dialog open</guilabel> checkboxes are
both checked.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Up/Down</keysym>: Brings back and forth command history in text dialog box
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-FontMgr">
<title>Font Style Manager</title>

<para>
Font management is the area where NsCDE and CDE are probably most different.
Font Style Manager is completely NsCDE tool to set fonts for usage inside
FVWM and external toolkits integration (X Resources/Motif, GTK2, GTK3,
Qt4, Qt5 ...).
</para>
<para>
NsCDE defines 15 fonts. Five groups with three members:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Normal Small
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Normal Medium
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Normal Large
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Bold Small
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Bold Medium
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Bold Large
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Italic Small
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Italic Medium
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Italic Large
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Monospaced Small
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Monospaced Medium
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Monospaced Large
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Monospaced Bold Small
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Monospaced Bold Medium
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Monospaced Bold Large
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
This fonts are defined as FVWM <emphasis>infostore</emphasis> variables in
<filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/NsCDE-Font-$DPI.conf</filename> and/or in
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Font-$DPI.conf</filename>.
Further, they are defined as CPP macros in
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xdefaults.fontdefs</filename> which is included in
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xdefaults</filename>
where it is used. GTK2 and GTK3 are also getting default font (Normal Medium) in
their configurations if integration option has been selected in Font Style Manager.
X resources and GTK are not refreshed by default, their checkboxes must be selected
by the user.
</para>

<para>
The Font Style Manager itself consists of fontsets and fonts. Fontsets are
named complete sets of five groups of three members of fonts defined above.
Fontsets are stored in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/share/fontsets</filename> and in
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/fontsets</filename>. If font set is selected in
Font Style Manager, 15 fonts from the set are loaded into preview lists of the application and can be
immediately applied or further customized before saving as
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Font-$DPI.conf</filename>. Fontsets are on the leftmost GUI list and
inactive until button <guilabel>Use Selected Font Set</guilabel> is not clicked.
Manual font selection contains list of XFT fonts found on the system in the
middle list and their styles (regular, bold, italic ...) on the rightmost
list.
</para>
<para>
Fonts can be set for the current DPI, or custom predefined DPI can be set. If
custom DPI is set, fonts configuration file will change in <varname>$DPI</varname> part of the
name.
</para>
<para>
Main font selectors are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Preview Set For Size
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Font Group
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Font Size
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
First popup menu loads 5 fonts from one of the 3 sets: small, medium or large.
Second popup determines on which font current selection is working (normal,
bold, italic, mono, mono bold), and third popup menu sets font size.
When Font Style Manager is started, current configuration is loaded and fonts
selected for a preview.
</para>
<para>
Button <guibutton>Default</guibutton> loads
<filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/share/fontsets/Default_$DPI.fontset</filename> which can
then be saved or further customized. Bottom half of the Font Style Manager
contains preview for all fonts from the one of the three selected size
sets.
</para>
<para>
Checkboxes <guilabel>Refresh Gtk2/Gtk3</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Refresh X Resources"</guilabel>
are integrating font selection with popular widgets by providing variable normal medium font and
it's size to their configuration files. Qt4 and Qt5 should automatically pick
Gtk fonts if GTK2 font engine is active in their configurations. If not,
<command>qtconfig-qt4</command> and <command>qt5ct</command> applications can be started and
some minor changes done and undone - enough for Apply/Save to take effect, and then font from Gtk will
be loaded for sure. Checkbox <guilabel>Run User Script</guilabel> will attempt to run
<command>$FVWM_USERDIR/libexec/fontmgr.local</command> if exists, with arguments of the new
config file and current DPI. This is intended for user's customizations which
are currently beyond NsCDE's scope of integrations.
</para>

<para>
<guibutton>Save</guibutton> button will save configuration of fonts and ask user to immediately
restart FVWM, while <guibutton>Save Font Set</guibutton> will first save configuration as a new
fontset and then as active configuration. In that way, further experiments
with fonts can be done by the user, but saved fontset from some good point can
be loaded to replace current configuration. When <guibutton>Use Selected Font Set</guibutton> is
clicked, list of the fontsets becomes active, and lists of fonts and their
styles inactive. Once font set is clicked, it will load preview of all the
fonts in the fontset and the same button which is now called <guibutton>Select Fonts
Manually</guibutton> can be clicked for further customizations. Mentioned button will
change back it's title to <guibutton>Use Selected Font Set</guibutton>.
Button <guibutton>Close</guibutton> discards actions, and
<guibutton>Help</guibutton> button will call help text (if implemented).
</para>
<para>
Configuration of fonts can be totally reset and discarded by removing file
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Font-$DPI.conf</filename> and FVWM restarted.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Font Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-KeyboardMgr">
<title>Keyboard Style Manager</title>
<para>
Keyboard Style Manager tool can be used to set (xset) 4 values:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Auto Repeat on/off
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Start Delay (start of repeat delay)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Repeat Delay
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Click Volume
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
This values are standard xset(1) <emphasis>r</emphasis> and <emphasis>c</emphasis> subcommands
and their values, minimal and maximal allowed values are (or should be in most cases) the same
in GUI as they are in command line tool.
</para>
<para>
<guibutton>Default</guibutton> button will set auto repeat to on, start rate to 512, repeat delay to
16 and click volume to 50.
</para>
<para>
<guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button applies setting in runtime, while <guibutton>Save</guibutton>
button writes <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xset.conf</filename> file which is a generated
<command>xset</command> command batch executed during startup.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Keyboard Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Keyboard Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-OccupyWorkspace">
<title>Occupy Workspace</title>
<para>
This tool dialog is called from the left titlebar button menu. Or from
<keysym>Alt+Space</keysym> key combination from the window context. It is exact copy of the
same CDE dialog and it sends selected window to workspace selected from the list, or it can
make it sticky with <guibutton>All Workspaces</guibutton> checkbox pressed in. One addition here
is the checkbox <guibutton>Go With the Window</guibutton>; when checked, makes NsCDE to change
a current workspace and go where window was sent. <guibutton>OK</guibutton> performs an action,
<guibutton>Dismiss</guibutton> quits Occupy Workspace tool.
</para>
<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Occupy Workspace without performing an action.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>H</keysym>: Displays this help text, like <guibutton>Help</guibutton> was pressed.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>A</keysym>: Checks <guilabel>All Workspaces</guilabel> checkbox.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Return</keysym>: Performs move action like OK button was pressed, without going to the
selected workspace.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Return</keysym>: Performs move action like OK button was pressed, and changes active
workspace to the same destination.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Up/Down</keysym>: Selects workspace in the up or down direction on the list.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-PointerMgr">
<title>Mouse Style Manager</title>
<para>
Mouse Style Manager tool manages pointer - that is, mouse settings. It's
duties are few more than only xset(1) <emphasis>m</emphasis> command. Namely:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Mouse acceleration (xset)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Threshold (xset)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Double-Click
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Handedness (xmodmap)
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
Acceleration and Threshold are standard xset(1) <emphasis>m</emphasis> options
and man page for xset(1) should be consulted.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Handedness</emphasis> can be set to flip left and right mouse button functions, while
<emphasis>Double Click</emphasis> is in fact most complex: it has test area where user can test
double click speed (pixmap will change on double-click success), and this
setting is changing:
</para>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 FVWM MenuStyle DoubleClick value (<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE.conf</filename>)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 X Resources multiClickTime resource in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xdefaults.mouse</filename>
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Qt/KDE settings in <filename>$HOME/.kde/share/config/kdeglobals</filename> (or similar path) if
  found
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Gtk2 (<filename>$HOME/.gtkrc-2.0</filename>) if file exists
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Gtk3 (<filename>$HOME/.config/gtk-3.0/settings.ini</filename>) if file exists
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
Double-Click value is in milliseconds in all mentioned configurations.
<guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button applies <command>xset</command> and
<command>xmodmap</command> values set in runtime, but not double-click settings.
</para>
<para>
<guibutton>Save</guibutton> button saves changes in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xset.conf</filename>
and all other optional files for widget and FVWM integration.
<guibutton>Default</guibutton> button will set handedness for right-handed, double-click on 450,
acceleration on 60, and threshold on 8, apply xset and xmodmap values, FVWM
<emphasis>MenuStyle</emphasis> <emphasis>DoubleClickTime</emphasis> and will warp pointer
to <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button for actions to be written in config files.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Mouse Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Mouse Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-PowerSaveMgr">
<title>Power Save Manager</title>
<para>
This tool manages screen DPMS values. It uses standard <command>xset(1)</command> to set screen
<emphasis>standby</emphasis>, <emphasis>suspend</emphasis> and <emphasis>off</emphasis> times.
Values are from 0 to 65535. Standby time cannot be bigger than suspend and/or off time, and
suspend time cannot be bigger than off time.
</para>
<para>
It has a checkbox which enables or disables DPMS management at all.
Values are written in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xset.conf</filename>.
</para>
<para>
If <filename>$HOME/.xscreensaver</filename> is present and has DPMS options
in it, they will be synchronized with xset <emphasis>dpms</emphasis> options
written in <filename>Xset.conf</filename>.
<guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button applies runtime (but not xscreensaver) while
<guibutton>Save</guibutton> button writes configuration file and <filename>$HOME/.xscreensaver</filename>
DPMS settings if this file exists. <guibutton>Default</guibutton> button will set the following defaults:
DPMS <emphasis>on</emphasis>, standby <emphasis>1200 seconds</emphasis>, suspend <emphasis>1800
seconds</emphasis>, and off time <emphasis>2400 seconds</emphasis>, apply this settings on runtime,
and point mouse to <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button for changes to be written.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Powersave Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Powersave Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-SubpanelMgr">
<title>Subpanel Manager</title>
<para>
Only in NsCDE. Tool written for managing FvwmButtons transient Subpanels which
are opened from the Front Panel. It is called from <emphasis>Install Icon</emphasis> action on
every Subpanel. This tool exists because FvwmButtons doesn't implement drag
and drop, and there is no application manager present, since this part of CDE
functions cannot be easy implemented even if some file manager is taken to act
as application manager.
</para>
<para>
Subpanel Manager has a list of all applications which are providing system menu
with it's presence (patched version of fvwm-menu-desktop is used in the
background), and the list of applications provided in the current Subpanel from
which tool is called by "Install Icon".
This lists are displayed on the top of the window side by side: system menu
applications on the left, and current Subpanel items on the right list.
There are 3 text fields: <guilabel>Name</guilabel>, <guilabel>Command</guilabel>
and <guilabel>Icon File</guilabel>. This fields are
automatically populated when some item from mentioned lists is clicked, but it
can also be populated manually if user wishes to add a custom application,
Fvwm Module, Fvwm Function or other entry manually on the Subpanel.
Special type of "Check for ..." is meant for entries which in command field are
defining for the first command something common like shell, <command>env</command> etc.
If we want to override a pointless check existance for this, and define other command
string for checking, popdown menu option <guilabel>Check for ...</guilabel> can be selected,
and small text field below popdown menu will appear, where this command can be specified.
Subpanel Manager can also remove existing entries from the Subpanel.
</para>
<para>
Subpanel Manager implements this helper functions for modifying and applying
settings on new items:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Type (exec, module, function, other, check-for)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Do not check for command existence</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Icon indicator</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

<para>
To place some new application from the left (all applications) list in exact place
on the subpanel, select an existing entry on the subpanel (right) list. When left
arrow button is clicked, new application will appear on the list exactly below that
one which has been previously selected, otherwise, default is to place new entries
as second entry on the subpanel's list of applications.
</para>

<para>
Click on the icon indicator will open simple file browser which can be used to find,
see as preview, and set icon for manual entries which are not part of the applications
list, or an alternative icon for program from applications list.
<guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button regenerates subpanel, while <guibutton>Save</guibutton>
button does this and also quits Subpanel Manager.
</para>

<para>
Subpanels configuration file <filename>Subpanels.actions</filename>, can be edited by
hand in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> if something needs to be changed on existing
entries. If editing by hand, <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/generate_subpanels</command>
must be used to generate FVWM configuration output which must be redirected into
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Subpanels.conf</filename>.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Subpanel Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Subpanel Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-SubpanelSettings">
<title>Subpanel Settings</title>
<para>
A small helper dialog with functions to change display name of the subpanel,
width of the subpanel if titles require wider (or short ones narrower) panel
frame, end enabled/disabled state of the subpanel.
Button <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> will erase user configuration and load
system default one for given subpanel. Name, width and enablement all have
their own <guibutton>Default</guibutton> button right of the text field. If pressed, it will load
system defaults for name, width and subpanel's enablement state. All buttons are doing
in memory changes until <guibutton>OK</guibutton> is pressed,
except <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> button which acts immediately.
<guibutton>Close</guibutton> button closes dialog without changes except if <guibutton>Reset</guibutton>
has been pressed. This dialog is called from subpanel menu which can be
popped with the left (and only) button on subpanel's titlebar. It is called
<guilabel>Subpanel Settings</guilabel>. It reloads configuration of the given subpanel after
applying changes and exiting with <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Subpanel Settings.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Subpanel Settings.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-SysActionDialog">
<title>System Action Dialog</title>
<para>

This is the login/logout form with the possibilities to reboot or shutdown the
system, or change X session. It has also options for suspend/sleep (S3), hybrid suspend,
and hibernation of the system. Of course, <command>reboot</command>, <command>shutdown</command>,
<command>pm-suspend</command>, <command>pm-hybrid-suspend</command> and
<command>pm-hibernate</command> will work only if
<command>sudo</command> entries are configured properly. While System Action Dialog is active,
root cursor changes to line-crossed cursor which is dismissed after the action is performed or
dialog action dismissed.
In <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/doc/examples/sudo</filename>, one can find example
which can be put in <filename class="directory">/etc/sudoers.d</filename> with little changes.
<guibutton>Confirm</guibutton> button applies, <guibutton>Dismiss</guibutton> cancels and
closes the dialog.

</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits System Action Dialog without performing any action.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Same as <guibutton>Escape</guibutton>
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Return</keysym>: Performs an action as if <guibutton>Confirm</guibutton> is pressed.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Up/Down</keysym>: Changes between 7 possible options of System Action Dialog's popup menu.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-SysInfo">
<title>Sysinfo</title>
<para>

Copy of the Sun Solaris <emphasis>Workstation Information</emphasis> info dialog.
It doesn't have any functions apart <guibutton>close (Dismiss)</guibutton> button. It's
role is informational. It displays current username, hostname, machine
and CPU architecture type. IP address, hostid, network (NIS, NISPLUS,
LDAP ...) domain name, internet domain name, size of the physical RAM,
swap size, swap usage (as progressbar), operating system long name, and
then version of the FVWM and version of the NsCDE. Last it shows time
when system was last booted. This dialog can be found on the <emphasis>System</emphasis>
or fourth Subpanel of the Front Panel in default configuration, under
the entry <emphasis>Workstation Info</emphasis>.
In the context of it's window, keys <keysym>Escape</keysym>, <keysym>Return</keysym> and
<keysym>Q</keysym> will close a window.

</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-WindowMgr">
<title>Window Style Manager</title>
<abstract>
<para>
In the beginning, this GUI tool has been exact copy of the CDE
<link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link>.
In a way, this was bad. While providing exact copy of the same named
CDE tool. It was ignoring the fact we are using FVWM as a WM and
framework for NsCDE, and FVWM has couple hundred more options, and it
is tens times more powerful than CDE's dtwm, and probably the
main reason for combining CDE look and (partially) feel of CDE with
powerful new functionalities which are provided by FVWM and some 3rd
party programs.
</para>
<para>
On the other hand, writing a tool that will handle ALL fvwm options and write that
in FvwmScript which not much a powerful language can easily contain
tens of thousands lines of code, and yet be buggy and probably some
things will be impossible to do. Even then, it will be burden for
users to use and almost completely avoided.
</para>
<para>
A middle solution was provided: all from CDE original dialog, plus
some similar extended FVWM options, on the first tab, and other
important configurations on the rest three tabs. Tabs are implemented
as popup menu on the top right side of the window - choosing an option
from that menu changes displayed options - a poor man's tabs in a way.
Some of options provided by
<link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link> are not full set of
this options if configured manually in FVWM configuration, but for
needs of CDE clone this is more than enough.
</para>
</abstract>

<sect3 id="NsCDE-WindowMgr-Behavior">
<title>Configuration Section: Window Behavior</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Only Pointer Inside Window Makes Focus</guilabel>: this configures so called
<emphasis>MouseFocus</emphasis> as catch-all FVWM Style (*). See fvwm(1) for MouseFocus.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Point In Window To Make Active</guilabel>: this is FVWM <emphasis>SloppyFocus</emphasis>
Style option. This is default focus style. If you want more CDE behavior,
select MouseFocus option above. In SloppyFocus mode, pointer will make
focus on window while entering it, but will not lose focus while leaving
the window. See fvwm(1) for SloppyFocus.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Click In Window To Make Active</guilabel>: self-explanatory.
This is FVWM's ClickToFocus style.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Raise Window When Made Active</guilabel>: self explanatory. If selected,
focused window will be raised. This option will enable FvwmAuto
module instance with <parameter class="option">-mfocus</parameter> option. See fvwm(1) and FvwmAuto(1).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Allow Primary Windows On Top</guilabel>: this will allow window to lower it's
transient windows (popups and such). See fvwm(1) for <emphasis>RaiseTransient</emphasis>
and <emphasis>DontRaiseTransient</emphasis> styles.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Lower Transient With Primary Window</guilabel>: self explanatory. See fvwm(1)
for <emphasis>LowerTransient</emphasis> and <emphasis>DontLowerTransient</emphasis>
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Raise/Lower Primaries With Transients</guilabel>: if transient windows are
raised or lowered, primary windows goes with them. See fvwm(1) for
<emphasis>StackTransientParent</emphasis> and <emphasis>DontStackTransientParent</emphasis>
style options.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Show Contents During Move</guilabel>: weather window contents is visible or
not during window move. Default is a transparent frame with a grid.
See fvwm(1) for <emphasis>OpaqueMoveSize</emphasis>.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Time After Which Active Window Is Raised</guilabel>: if <guilabel>Raise Window When
Made Active</guilabel> is turned on, this option will be enabled and time in
milliseconds can be set here. See FvwmAuto(1).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Manual Window Movement Threshold</guilabel>: see fvwm(1) for a
<emphasis>MoveThreshold</emphasis> option. 5 pixels is the default.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="NsCDE-WindowMgr-Icons">
<title>Configuration Section: Window Icons</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Use Icon Box</guilabel>: if this option is selected, main FVWM configuration
in <filename>NsCDE-Main.conf</filename> will spawn <emphasis>FvwmIconBox</emphasis>
configured as close as possible as an alternative to icons of iconified windows.
Classic icons will be disabled. The rest of options in this "tab" will be disabled because
they do not apply anymore in this configuration. Note: FvwmIconBox has
not exactly the same functionality as CDE's Icon Box.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Place On Workspace</guilabel>: default. Icons of the windows will be placed
on the screen. By default, from top left to the direction bottom left.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Place Icons Left/Right from Bottom/Top to Top/Bottom</guilabel>: this four
exclusive options will direct icon placement on the screen. See
<emphasis>IconBox</emphasis> and <emphasis>IconFill</emphasis> options in fvwm(1) for more information.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Default Icon Size</guilabel>: in pixels. See <emphasis>IconSize</emphasis> in fvwm(1).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Maximum Icon Size</guilabel>: in pixels. See <emphasis>IconSIze</emphasis> in fvwm(1).
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="NsCDE-WindowMgr-Pageedges">
<title>Configuration Section: Page Edges</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

 <guilabel>Raise Front Panel On Page Change</guilabel>: as is says, when current active
page changes, Front Panel will be raised.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Pager Preview On Page Change</guilabel>:  on page change, spawn a small
transient FVWM pager called <emphasis>LocalPager</emphasis> on the top center of the
screen to indicate what is on the current desk - this is controlled by the infostore
variable in the $FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE.conf
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Disable Page Change On Screen Edge</guilabel>:  if selected, current page will
not change when pointer is longer time on the screen edge. In this mode,
active page must be changed by other means (keyboard shortcuts, WSM
submenus, PGM, left click on 1st titlebar button ...)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Page Change On Screen Edge (1px)</guilabel>:  default internal detector of the
screen edge. Do not change this if it is working.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Page Change On Screen Edge (2px)</guilabel> If FVWM has a problem with X server
and page change does not work smooth, use this option as a safe
alternative. See fvwm(1).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Page Edge Resistance</guilabel>:  how many milliseconds FVWM waits on the screen
edge area for an page change action to be taken. Default is 380.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Edge Window Move Resistance</guilabel>:  similar as Page  Edge Resistance, but
for move operation - how hard it should be to move a window between pages.
Defaults to 80 pixels.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Edge Window Move Delay</guilabel>:  time to wait to consider moved window for page
change in the first place (to start counting pixels of the Edge Window Move
Resistance). Defaults to 320 pixels.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="NsCDE-WindowMgr-Animations">
<title>Configuration Section: Animation</title>
<para>
This tab controls behavior of the FvwmAnimate. See FvwmAnimate(1).
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Animate Window Iconification</guilabel>:  on/off of the FvwmAnimate module.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Animation Effect</guilabel>:  See FvwmAnimate(1)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Animation Frame Delay</guilabel>: See FvwmAnimate(1)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Animation Revolution Twist</guilabel>: See FvwmAnimate(1)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Outline Width</guilabel>: See FvwmAnimate(1)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 <guilabel>Animation Iterations</guilabel>: See FvwmAnimate(1), be careful on virtual displays
with a bad video driver. It can behave really slower than on host system with
the same parameters.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="NsCDE-WindowMgr-Misc">
<title>Misc Window Style Manager Functions</title>
<para>
Button <guibutton>Default</guibutton> on the top right edge of the window will read
system defaults into options and they will be set in permanent configuration if
<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button is pressed afterwards.
</para>
<para>
<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button applies changes to <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE.conf</filename>.
<guibutton>Dismiss</guibutton> button will close the window without making any changes.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Window Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Window Style Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-WsPgMgr">
<title>Workspaces and Pages Manager (WsPgMgr)</title>
<para>
This tool is specific to NsCDE. It configures three things:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Number of virtual desktops
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Names of virtual desktops
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Number of virtual pages
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
This graphical tool writes files <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/WSM.conf</filename>
and <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE.conf</filename>.
On the top of the window is graphical representation of the Workspace
Manager. Every button when clicked becomes editable and it's name can
be changed (pres <keysym>return</keysym> on the text field after writing new name).
This change will be written immediately WITHOUT pressing <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button.
Name of the desk will be changed across all NsCDE and FVWM (WSM, Occupy
Workspace, menus etc) after window manager restart is triggered with <guibutton>OK</guibutton>
button. In NsCDE, there are 4 options for desks: 2, 4, 6 and 8 desks.
FVWM itself supports infinite number, but in NsCDE care must be taken
about presentation of this desks in various applets and tools.
Nevertheless, theoretically even in NsCDE with maximum number of desks
multiplied with maximum number of pages, user can get 128 work spaces
which is probably enough (too much) for 99% of the people.
</para>
<para>
Number of vertical and horizontal pages can also be configured here.
This change will affect Page Manager (PGM), and menus which are displaying
pages. Page names are not configurable via GUI. User is encouraged to
open <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/WSM.conf</filename> and edit to suit.
</para>
<para>
<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button saves configuration, restarts window manager and quits.
<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button discards, except if new names of desks are set, because
this is written immediately, but window manager is not restarted.
Workspaces and Pages Manager is called from the Front Panel's small
left button menu which is called when that button is clicked with the right
pointer button.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Workspaces and Pages Manager.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Ctrl+Q</keysym>: Quits Workspaces and Pages Manager.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Helper-Dialogs">
<title>Helper Dialogs</title>
<sect2 id="NsCDE-ActionForm">
<title>ActionForm - FvwmScript</title>
<para>
Dialog which uses custom text and asks user for action.
Action is then executed (<guibutton>OK</guibutton>) or aborted (<guibutton>Dismiss</guibutton>).
Example of usage is restart dialog. Application must
provide in argument vector question text, title text, buttons text,
and buttons actions when calling this dialog.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-ChoiceForm">
<title>ChoiceForm - FvwmScript</title>
<para>
Similar as ActionForm, but button actions are not provided in command
line, but signal about chosen action is sent to the calling program
("father" FvwmScript usually).
Used only in <link linkend="NsCDE-FontMgr">Font Style Manager</link> for now.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-FilePicker">
<title>FilePicker - FvwmScript</title>
<para>
A simple file pick open/save dialog. Copy of FVWM file picker,
but with added option to display a file if file is an icon. It is a
simple file browser with <guibutton>up</guibutton> and <guibutton>home</guibutton> shortcuts,
path view and <guibutton>show/hide</guibutton> button for hidden (files starting with a dot) files.
</para>
<para>
Used in <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr"> Backdrop</link> Style Manager, Subpanel Manager,
and <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>
for adding backdrops, photos, icons and palettes.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-InputForm">
<title>InputForm - FvwmScript</title>
<para>
Form with text field which asks user to name something. If <guibutton>OK</guibutton> is
pressed, string is sent to the parent script for further processing.
Used in <link linkend="NsCDE-FontMgr">Font Style Manager</link>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-WaitNotice">
<title>WaitNotice - FvwmScript</title>
<para>
Short lived simple FvwmScript form, butonless and with a 3 slots for text.
This dialog serves as short information if some NsCDE action is started which
is not immediately obvious in a 1-2 seconds. It will appear in the middle of the
screen with a bigger font and relief text and live between half of the second till
5 seconds. Depending with which text and duration time it was called by some function
or other FvwmScript program. If clicked or receives return or escape key, it will
dissapear immediately.
</para>
<para>
Used by <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>,
SysActionDialog and a documetation view function
<filename>f_DisplayURL</filename>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-NColorsDialog">
<title>NColorsDialog - FvwmScript</title>
<para>
A <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> part
</para>
<para>
Helper dialog to select 4, 8 or default color scheme in
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>.
It changes number of colors while browsing, previewing or
choosing a color theme.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Dialog.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-PaletteDialog">
<title>PaletteDialog - FvwmScript</title>
<para>
A <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link> part
</para>
<para>
Helper dialog which provides a list of palettes to the <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop
Style Manager</link> when user wants to use color schemes from another
palette from currently used in user's setup. This is NsCDE addon
functionality, not present in original CDE. Additionally,
background variants from custom palettes can be used too as from
the default user's palette in 8-color mode, which is also NsCDE
feature not present in original CDE.
</para>

<para>
Key Bindings:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
<keysym>Escape</keysym>: Quits Dialog.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Backdrops-Palettes-Fonts">
<title>Backdrops, Palettes and Fonts</title>
<para>
Together  with Workspace Manager, Backdrops and Palettes are probably most
known things in CDE by which it is visually recognized.
</para>
<para>
Backdrops, as many probably know are relatively simple XPM textures and
pictures consisting usualy from 2-5 <emphasis>base</emphasis> colors: <emphasis>background</emphasis>,
<emphasis>foreground</emphasis>, <emphasis>selectColor</emphasis>,
<emphasis>topShadowColor</emphasis>, and <emphasis>bottomShadowColor</emphasis>.
This colors are taken from the current (or custom) palette and applied to the symbolic
definition of colors in XPM templates. Backdrop is then generated, tiled and
applied to the root window. Every desk can have it's own backdrop texture. In
4 colors mode of the palette theme, they are all colored in the same pattern,
while in 8 colors mode, every desk from 1-4 has it's own color variant from
the current palette. If there are more that four desks defined, fifth is
repeated color of the first, sixth of the second and so on.
</para>
<para>
Here, in addition to original CDE textures, there are some 100 new and custom
textures created from (free and public) textures which were convenient for
this customization. In other words, NsCDE implements more than 100 backdrops,
and with Backdrop Style Manager user can import to it's
<filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/backdrops</filename> it's own backdrops,
or put them there with terminal or file manager.
</para>
<para>
Backdrops must have alternative extension for X Pixmaps: that is, not <emphasis>.xpm</emphasis>,
but <emphasis>.pm</emphasis>.
</para>
<para>
If one wants their custom backdrop to be dynamic with palette/theme of NsCDE,
one must edit them to set symbolic names of the colors described above. See
existing backdrops to get an idea. Apart from symbolic names, backdrops also
have a real color defined to be compatible with XPM specification, but values of
this colors can be arbitrary, since they are not used if symbolic name on the
same line is set.
</para>
<para>
Default backdrops are set from the
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/defaults/backer</filename> until
user does not redefine/set his own with
<link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link>. Default
palette is <emphasis>Broica</emphasis> in 8 colors variant.
</para>
<para>
Backdrops generated by <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style manager</link> are put in user's
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/backer/DeskN-&lt;backdropname&gt;.pm</filename> and defined in
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Backdrops.conf</filename> as colorsets of
<emphasis>TiledPixmap</emphasis> type. NsCDE reserved FVWM colorsets numbers for backdrops
are from 31-38 for all eight possible desktops.
This file is read by FvwmBacker(1) FVWM module. It is automatically generated when user makes
first change with <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link>.
</para>
<para>
Until then, file <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/NsCDE-Backdrops.conf</filename> is read, which
itself reads pre-generated and pre-defined backdrops from the
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/defaults/backer</filename> directory.
</para>
<para>
We can conclude that backdrops are source form or template file, and when processed
with color values from the palette, this backdrop's final form is, ready to be set by FvwmBacker(1).
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Configuration-Files">
<title>Configuration files explained</title>
<abstract>
<para>
As pointed above, NsCDE has a quite complex set of configuration
files. ~ 90% of them are the FVWM configurations. But, this system
of configurations is arranged in some logical and consistent way.
For example, keyboard shortcuts in NsCDE-Keybindings.conf,
FvwmBacker configuration in NsCDE-Backer.conf, (generated)
colorsets in NsCDE-Colorset.conf etc.
</para>
<para>
All this configurations are included from the NsCDE-Main.conf.
This is the starting FVWM configuration which sets core options
and safe defaults, and reads the rest of the configuration files
which are included there. It defines StartFunction which starts
all additional modules and calls important things during start
or restart of the Window Manager. System Wide configuration files
are located in $NSCDE_ROOT/config, while user local hooks or
user complete overrides are in $FVWM_USERDIR.
</para>
</abstract>
<para>
This is default list of system-wide configurations:
</para>

<sect2 id="FrontPanel_actions">
<title>FrontPanel.actions</title>
<para>
This is not a FVWM file. Lines in this file are default actions
and icons for Front Panel. This file is parsed from the <command>fpexec</command>
and <command>fpseticon</command> shell scripts. All or individual entries from this
file can be overridden by creating <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/FrontPanel.actions</filename>
file. This is a CSV-like file (comma is a field separator), and it defines main 10
buttons of the Front Panel, their actions and icons.
</para>
<para>
File format is:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Button Number (Btn1, Btn2, BtnN ...)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Icon path (FVWM relative from ImagePath)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mouse Button (3 mouse buttons for 3 different actions if needed)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Program executable to check for or <emphasis>NOCHK</emphasis> for check
 avoidance</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Actions (commands) with options and arguments to the end of the line</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
After editing this file (system-wide or user's) nothing needs to be
reloaded because file is read from the <function>f_FrontPanelAction</function> function
on every click on every icon on the Front Panel.
There is no GUI tool for managing this file yet.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Animate_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Animate.conf</title>
<para>
FVWM Animate Module configuration. Animate module is started by NsCDE by
default automatically, but with <emphasis>None</emphasis> as a default effect. This can be
reconfigured by the user in private <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Animate.conf</filename>
(or <filename>.local</filename>) with editor or with Window Style Manager. None effect is choosen
as default for increased CDE similarity, because CDE doesn't have iconification
animation effects.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Auto_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Auto.conf</title>
<para>
Configuration of the <emphasis>FvwmAuto</emphasis> module and provided is a private set of
FVWM functions from which only <function>f_AutoHide</function> (and parent functions) are
used currently. FvwmAuto is started by NsCDE by default i <option>-menter</option>
mode from <filename>NsCDE-Main.conf</filename>. Currently used to autoraise and autohide
Front Panel, no matter which focus style is selected by default. In
that way, Front Panel is not in the way of applications, yet on mousover
action it is raised and lowered when it is not in focus and not use. FvwmAuto
can be used to autoshade or autoiconify Front Panel and much more. See
FvwmAuto(1).
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Backdrops_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Backdrops.conf</title>
<para>
This file defines 8 colorsets for all (maximal) 8 desktops as a <emphasis>TiledPixmap</emphasis>
colorset type. In the system configuration, static non-generated
configuration defines pre-generated default backdrops of default <emphasis>Broica</emphasis>
color scheme. When user makes the first change with <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style
Manager</link>, user's private copy of this file is created in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>.
In NsCDE, colorsets 31 - 38 are reserved for backdrops (or png, xpm
photos).
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Backer_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Backer.conf</title>
<para>
Rarely needed in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>. FvwmBacker(1) configuration which defines
8 maximum desks and refers them to 8 colorsets from 31 - 38. Option
<option>RetainPixmap</option> is defined in case user wants to use X compositor such as
compton(1) with NsCDE.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Banner_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Banner.conf</title>
<para>
FvwmBanner(1) configuration. Displays logo during login.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Colorset_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Colorset.conf</title>
<para>
Definition of all colorsets minus colorsets 31 - 38 which are reserved for the
backdrops. System-wide file has predefined color values for default
color scheme (Broica), while user's file in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> is created on first
change made with <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>. Apart from FVWM colorsets, this
file exports in environment two variables: <varname>NSCDE_PALETTE</varname> with the name
of the color palette used in generation of the file, and
<varname>NSCDE_PALETTE_NCOLORS</varname> which is either 4 or 8, depending which color
variant has been used in <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE_conf">
<title>NsCDE.conf</title>
<para>
This file defines various FVWM and NsCDE defaults. System wide
configuration are static defaults which can be loaded by
<link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link> or by erasing user's copy of the file.
User's copy of the <filename>NsCDE.conf</filename> contains all options
(minus FvwmAnimate) from <link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager's</link> set of options,
but it has some options such as FVWM <emphasis>infostore</emphasis> variables for
default terminal and file manager applications, graphical editor, and
such. Infostore variables <varname>desknum</varname>,
<varname>pagematrixX</varname> and <varname>pagematrixY</varname> are
managed by the Workspace and Pages Manager while
<varname>menudclicktm</varname> infostore
variable is managed by the Pointer Style Manager. In <filename>NsCDE.conf</filename>, defaults
for page edges, focus, icons, and such are defined. See <xref linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr"/>
 and fvwm(1) for details. Since this is read by FVWM,
user can set in this file local variables and additional configuration
options if needful, which are not covered in other parts of the
configuration. While applications are taking great care with long regexp
lines to parse and write this file, if edited manually, user is advised
to keep it clean: use proper capitalization as it is described in
fvwm(1), without line breaks and if possible, surplus spaces and tabs.
Comments are allowed as usual: as lines which begins with <emphasis>#</emphasis> sign.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Event_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Event.conf</title>
<para>
FvwmEvent(1) module configuration. In this file a single instance of the
FvwmEvent called <option>MainLoop</option> is defined. It passes ID (Window ID, desk
etc ... depending on context) for window manager actions. <option>Cmd</option> option is
empty: FVWM functions are used for all defined actions. Currently,
actions <option>new_desk</option>, <option>new_page</option>, <option>add_window</option>
and <option>focus_change</option> are observed and
their respective functions from <filename>NsCDE-Functions.conf</filename> are triggered.
This serves Workspace Manager,
Page Manager (PGM) and window placement functions in an important way. If
redefined or disabled, things will start to break. It can be extended by
the user to suit the needs, but here also care must be taken, because
complex functions, or calling slow and/or resource hungry commands from
that functions can make FVWM (and hence NsCDE) dramatically slow.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Font-DPIdpi_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Font-$DPIdpi.conf</title>
<para>
... where $DPI is either 120, 144, 75 or 96.
</para>
<para>
This files are static when system wide, but generated by <link linkend="NsCDE-FontMgr">Font Style
Manager</link> in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>.
Every X server's <emphasis>DPI state</emphasis> selects and reads one
of this files - the one which exactly or approximately matches current
DPI in this order:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>if DPI is &lt;= 85, $DPI is 75</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>if DPI is &gt; 85 and &lt; 108, $DPI is 96</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>if DPI is &gt;= 108 and &lt; 132, $DPI is 120</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>if DPI is &gt;= 132, $DPI is 144</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Font sizes in configs are defined as infostore variables and used across
FVWM config files, an provided to FvwmScript programs with <command>getfont</command>
wrapper. Font sizes are in points. While defining them in pixels
(pixelsize=) will be easier, and all this care about DPI will not be
needed, integration with GTK2 and GTK3 in best of my knowledge and
research does not provide a way to define fonts in pixel sizes, so
either font sizes in points or unsure recalculation (again based on DPI)
will be needed while writing gtk settings.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Form_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Form.conf</title>
<para>
Definitions of few FVWM forms. FvwmForm is reading this. This are simple
popups and dialogs used in FvwmScripts and in part of the configuration.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-FrontPanel_conf">
<title>NsCDE-FrontPanel.conf</title>
<para>
Main NsCDE Front Panel configuration file. Here, FvwmButtons is
configured under the alias <option>*FrontPanel</option>. Special care is taken to place
most of configurable parts out of this file, so it doesn't have
to be forked into <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>, but this option nevertheless exists.
Here, all geometry, buttons, subpanels, default icons, frames and
widgets are written and put in place. This configuration, together with
swallowed WSM (Workspace Manager) is probably the most recognizable part
of the setup which provides us with familiar and so wanted CDE look - a
Front Panel. FvwButtons FrontPanel configuration is non-trivial, but it is very
trustworthy mimicking the original. Icon actions which user wants to change
here can be overridden with <filename>FrontPanel.actions</filename> file and
Subpanels which are also described here. Swallowed apps and "widgets" are
in most part already described in sections above.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Functions_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Functions.conf</title>
<para>
Another important part of the configuration. Almost all FVWM functions
are defined here, except 2-3 of core functions in NsCDE-Main.conf
which are reading the rest of the configuration. They are sorted in
logical groups and are used widely in almost every part of the
configuration, and particularly from the FvwmScript scripts. Main groups of NsCDE
FVWM functions are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Core Window Operation Functions</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Front Panel functions</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Misc core functions</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Functions called from FvwmEvent <option>MainLoop</option></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Functions for generating menus</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Placeholders for functions aimed for user to override</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Functions used in NsCDE FvwmScripts</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
For a FVWM function description see fvwm(1), in this file there is a
plethora of examples, and for user usage is the most interesting part
placeholders for functions which are here merely for programs to not
complain about missing them and which should be overridden in user's local
extension <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Functions.local</filename> - this extension file will
be read by the main configuration immediately after processing
<filename>NSCDE-Functions.conf</filename>. This functions are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
  <function>f_CheckMail</function>: called by CheckMailApplet on the FrontPanel on click
  and periodically. This is the place where some script can be called
  and with SendToModule to "1 1" (widget 1, routine 1) icon of empty
  mailbox will be changed to the icon of the full mailbox.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  <function>f_Calendar</function>: called by MonthDayApplet on click. Can be used to call
  external calendar application, to focus Thunderbird with lightning
  extension or whatever user finds useful.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  <function>f_Mixer</function>: unused currently.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  <function>f_AddCustomToRootMenu</function>: add custom entries in a convenient point of
  the root menu which is called by the right mouse button on the root
  window.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  <function>f_UserChangeDesk</function>: called when current active desk changes
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  <function>f_UserChangePage</function>: called when current active page changes
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Another useful function is conditional execution function <function>f_WarpOrExec</function>.
It takes 3+ arguments. First is the window name or class (or icon,
resource) name, second is the binary to check in <varname>$PATH</varname>>, and 3rd to the rest
of the command line is what to execute with all arguments included.
If window with name from arg1 is already present on <varname>$DISPLAY</varname>, it will
not be executed, but pointer will be simply pointed to that window.
If window was iconified, or function called from another desk or page,
window will be deiconified, and desk and/or current page changed to one where
existing window is residing.
</para>
<para>
Care must be taken if this file is overridden by the local copy of the
<emphasis>conf</emphasis> (not local) file, because a lot of things depends on this
functions.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-IconMan_conf">
<title>NsCDE-IconMan.conf</title>
<para>
If <guilabel>Use Icon Box</guilabel> option is selected in the
<link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link>,
infostore variable <varname>iconbox</varname> will be defined as non-zero, and
FvwmIconMan(1) module will be started on login from the <filename>NsCDE-Main.conf</filename>.
This file, <filename>NsCDE-IconMan.conf</filename> contains default configuration of that
module.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Ident_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Ident.conf</title>
<para>
Module FvwmIdent(1) is called either from a small menu which can be popped
up with middle pointer click on a titlebar, or from the root window
version of the <guilabel>Window Options</guilabel> menu. This is FvwmIdent's configuration
file. It simply defines colorset and font for the FvwmIdent's window.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Init_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Init.conf</title>
<para>
Most probable candidate for copying to <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>. Here are defined
start, quit and restart function (sessionless and session-managed)
which are internally recognized by FVWM during certain important
actions. <function>InitFunction</function> or
<function>SessionInitFunction</function> is the place to put all
user wants to be executed during NsCDE startup. In system-wide default
configuration there are already conditionally defined some probable
applications and there are hints and examples for user to customize this
further.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Keybindings_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Keybindings.conf</title>
<para>
For CDE clone and CDE compatibility, key bindings are a bit problematic area. In my local
installation of open sourced CDE in virtual machine with CentOS 7,
(didn't bothered to install Solaris 10 to examine their flavor again), key
bindings are almost non-existent. <keysym>Alt+F4</keysym> usually closes the window and
that's it. Because of this fact, and because NsCDE is not only a visual
clone of the CDE, but it aims to provide more functionality and to be
useful <emphasis>daily driver</emphasis> for user to enjoy in familiar look and feel (hated
by a lot of people) and to be seriously productive in the same time,
comfortable and quick, to have good graphic (such as anti-aliased fonts,
but this also can be turned off), a set of useful key bindings is
defined by default. This default keybindings set can be extended, partially
overridden, or completely replaced (copy the <filename>NsCDE-Keybinding.conf</filename> in
<varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> and edit, or even write from scratch). Defaults are
author's <emphasis>daily driver</emphasis>. For explanation what is the context, and what
modifier, see FVWM explanation (copied from original default FVWM
config and extended a bit). Namely:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
  cursor keys <keysym>up</keysym>, <keysym>down</keysym>,
  <keysym>left</keysym> and <keysym>right</keysym> with ctrl modifier are
    moving viewport from page to page in any context.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  the same combination, but with <keysym>meta</keysym> (<keysym>mod4</keysym>) is moving viewport by
    4% of the screen. (<keysym>Ctrl</keysym> moves 100%)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  the same combination, but with <keysym>shift</keysym> modifier moves mouse by 1%
    of the screen
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Ctrl+Meta+cursor keys</keysym> are changing first 4 desks
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+Shift+cursor keys</keysym> are moving currently focused window
    between first four desks
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Menu (Compose)</keysym> key pops up root menu in any context
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+Menu</keysym> combination pops up window operations menu
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Ctrl+Menu</keysym> moves Root Pager (if enabled) beneath the pointer or 
    iconifies Local Pager if LocalPager already has the pointer - toggle
    action
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Ctrl+ISO_Level3_Shift</keysym> (right alt) moves Root Pager (if enabled) beneath
    the pointer or iconifies Local Pager if LocalPager already has the pointer
    - a toggle action
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Shift+Menu</keysym> pops up Window List of all windows on the current desk
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Space</keysym> under icon frame pops up icon-specific contextual menu
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Key <keysym>Alt+Space</keysym> in the context of the window, frame corners, frame
    sides, title bar and icon (ovoids root window context!) calls
    Occupy Space dialog for window moving between the desks.
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Key <keysym>Meta+Space</keysym> in the context of the window, frame corners, frame
    sides and a title bar pops up Window Options context menu
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Key <keysym>Meta+Space</keysym> in the context of the icon, pops up Icon Options
    context menu
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Key <keysym>Alt+Insert</keysym> will give a focus to the last opened window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Key <keysym>Meta+Insert</keysym> will warp a pointer and give a focus to the last opened window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Key <keysym>Alt+BackSpace</keysym> will give a focus to the previously focused window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Key <keysym>Meta+BackSpace</keysym> will warp a pointer and give a focus to the previously focused window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F1</keysym> regenerates and refreshes the window
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F2</keysym> iconifies (deiconifies if in icon context)
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F3</keysym> "shades" or rolls up the window to titlebar only view
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F4</keysym> enters resize mode which can be finished with cursors keys
    and enter
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F5</keysym> enters move mode which can be finished with cursors keys
    and enter
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F6</keysym> raises or lowers the window
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F7</keysym> maximizes window 100% (whole screen + decorations)
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F8</keysym> maximizes window ~ 80% - avoids Front Panel
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F9</keysym> is empty
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F10</keysym> deletes a window (see fvwm(1))
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+Alt+F10</keysym> closes a window
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Shift+Meta+Alt+F10</keysym> forcefully destroys a window
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F11</keysym> is empty
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+F12</keysym> calls xrefresh
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Ctrl+Shift+Tab</keysym> Will open WindowList in the middle of the screen for a current workspace (desk)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Shift+Tab</keysym> Will open WindowList in the middle of the screen for all workspaces (desks)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+Tab</keysym> is cycling trough pages of the active desk from up to down
  and then right up to down
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+Tab</keysym> is cycling trough the all workspaces (desks)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+Alt+L</keysym> activates screensaver, that is, locks the screen
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+Alt+Insert</keysym> takes a screenshot of the root window with 200 ms delay
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F1</keysym> invokes default terminal app ($[infostore.terminal])
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F2</keysym> invokes Exec dialog
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F3</keysym> toggles visibility of the titlebar
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F4</keysym> toggles window's sticky state
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F6</keysym> saves geometry information for a current window in GeoDB.ini
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F7</keysym> centers the window in the middle of the screen
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F8</keysym> reads <filename>GeoDB.ini</filename> and if it finds an entry for the current
    resolution and <varname>$[w.class],</varname> it resizes and moves a window according to
    the specification in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR/GeoDB.ini</varname> 
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+F9</keysym> in the context of the known terminal application windows
    scratches the window to some 75%x72% of the screen, which is also a
    menu option in this windows called <emphasis>Wide Terminal</emphasis>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Ctrl+Escape</keysym> will raise Front Panel and reposition it to it's default
    place on the screen
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Shift+Escape</keysym> will do the same as <keysym>Ctrl+Escape,</keysym> but Front Panel is
    after repositioning shaded to bottom border of the screen. Invoking
    this key sequence again will unshade the Front Panel. Middle mouse
    button on the borders of the frame has the same effect
    </para>
    <para>
    Dynamic: defined in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/Keymenu.actions</filename>
    for automatic description on menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Alt+Escape</keysym> outside of the Front Panel focus will give Front Panel a focus and
  warp pointer in the middle of the Front Panel. If focus plus pointer is already on the  Front Panel
  previous window will be selected for the focus and pointer warped in the center of that window.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Meta+Escape</keysym> will call transient GlobalPager in any context. When clicked, this
Pager will close itself.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the context of the Front Panel, <keysym>Alt + 1-10</keysym> will pop up subpanels 1 to 10
and warp pointer to it
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the context of the any subpanel, <keysym>Alt + 1-10</keysym> will pop down this subpanel
and warp pointer to Front Panel
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="Keymenu_actions">
<title>Keymenu.actions</title>
<para>
This file is not FVWM configuration file. It is written
<link linkend="NsCDE-SubpanelSettings">Subpanel Settings</link>, or
manually with editor, and read by the <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/keymenu</command>
command which will generate infostore variables with descriptive keyboard shortcut names which
are used in NsCDE menus from <filename>NsCDE-Menus.conf</filename> and
<filename>NsCDE-Functions.conf</filename>, and additionaly, use the whole line after the keyword
in the first column with "Silent Key" prefix to dinamically generate this part of keybindings
which are separated from <filename>NsCDE-Keybindings.conf</filename> and processed specially
because they definition must automatically match keyboard binding description in various
menus.
</para>
<para>
The syntax of this file is simple: first column is the keyword which becomes infostore
variable (km_xrefresh as <varname>$[infostore.km_xrefresh]</varname>), and the rest columns of
every line is FVWM "Key" sintax which is paired with "Silent Key" prefix during initialization
with <function>f_KeyMenu -a</function> from <filename>NsCDE-Main.conf</filename>.
</para>
<para>
Every line, or dynamic keybinding can be overriden here if (re)defined in user's
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Keymeu.actions</filename>: whole file or just choosen keybindings.
The goal is to get their descriptions (after functions and menus reload) automatically in place
on menus. For example, "F3 A M" configuration for FVWM "Key" will become <keysym>Alt+F3</keysym>
description right of the <guilabel>(De)Shade</guilabel> item on titlebar left button popdown menu.
</para>
<para>
File Keymenu.actions is processed by <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/keymenu</command> script.
This script generates FVWM infostore variables used in menus, and executes FVWM "Key" commands
producing dynamic keybindings which are described in menus.
</para>
<para>
For a list of keybindings that are "dynamic", that is, not defined in
<filename>NsCDE-Keybindings.conf</filename>, but in <filename>Keymenu.actions</filename>, see
notices in section about <link linkend="NsCDE-Keybindings_conf">NsCDE-Keybindings.conf</link>.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Main_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Main.conf</title>
<para>
  Core configuration. This file is read the first upon starting FVWM
  Window Manager. In fact, FVWM is invoked with <option>-f /path/to/NsCDE-Main.conf</option>
  to read it instead of default FVWM system configuration or user's
  <filename>~/.fvwm/config</filename>.
  This invocation and configuration in <filename>NsCDE-Main.conf</filename>
  changes everything. It avoids <filename class="directory">~/.fvwm</filename> if user has a plain (normal)
  FVWM setup, defines and redefines FVWM internal variables and sets
  <varname>NSCDE_ROOT</varname>, configures some core FVWM options (like <option>DefaultIcon</option>),
  defines main FVWM <command>Read</command> command wrapper <function>f_ReadCfg</function>,
  sets desktop names, reads <filename>NsCDE.conf</filename> depending if user has it, or system-wide one,
  defines <function>StartFunction</function>, <option>DesktopSize</option>, and
  then reads most of the files
  described in this documents, composing NsCDE FVWM configuration.
  Care must be taken NOT to read this file with <function>f_ReadCfg</function>, because it
  will end up in the endless CPU hogging loop because <function>f_ReadCfg</function> will be
  destroyed and recreated during it's own execution. This file should
  probably never be overridden in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>. It is the init(8) of
  the NsCDE system.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Menus_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Menus.conf</title>
<para>
In NsCDE, there is a bunch of the menus. Root menus, contextual menus,
and even menus called or dinamically generated from FvwmScript(1).
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>MenuFvwmRoot</guimenuitem> built-in root menu of FVWM. As in CDE, menu of such
    type, it is called with a right click on the root window.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_Applications</guimenuitem> - main and dynamically generated menu with a python
    script <command>nscde-fvwm-menu-desktop</command> which is a modified version of the
    <command>fvwm-menu-desktop</command> (contains flat list of apps and icons for Front
    Panel's subpanels). It reads <filename>/etc/xdg/menus/&lt;desk&gt;-applications.menu</filename>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_QuickMenu</guimenuitem> beneath m_Applications. Empty by default. Intended to be
    destroyed and recreated by the user (<filename>NsCDE-Menus.local</filename>) with own
    favorites.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_NsCDEHelpMenu</guimenuitem> beneath Quick Menu. Contains links to this documentation
  in PDF and HTML forms.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_NsCDEMenu</guimenuitem> on the top of generated Applications menu.
  Contains entries to various the NsCDE internal tools.
  in PDF and HTML forms.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_MoveToPage</guimenuitem>: invoked from the 1st titlebar button. Moves window to
    the specified page on desk
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_MoveToWorkspace</guimenuitem>: as
  <guimenuitem>m_MoveToPage</guimenuitem>, but moves across desks. Invoked
    with middle pointer on the 1st titlebar button
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_ControlFrontPanelMenu</guimenuitem>: Front Panel specific functions. Invoked
    from the left top control panel menu button on right pointer click
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_DeiconifyOnPage</guimenuitem>: submenu of the main icon menu invoked with the
    1st pointer click on desktop icon, deiconify window on another page
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_FrontPanelWinMenu</guimenuitem>: Front Panel flavor of the
  <emphasis>Window Operations</emphasis>
    menu. Invoked from the top left menu button of the Front Panel
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_IconM2</guimenuitem>: calls small menu with FvwmIdent, xwininfo and xprop if
    icon is clicked with a middle pointer button
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_IconOps</guimenuitem>: main icon menu invoked with a click on the icon. Contains
    Icon flavor of the "Window Operations" menu, submenus (see above)
    and deiconify action
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_SubpanelWindowOps</guimenuitem>: a Subpanel flavor of the Window Operations
    menu. Invoked from the Subpanel's titlebar left (and only) button
    contains also contextual actions <guilabel>Refresh Subpanel</guilabel> and
    <guilabel>Subpanel Settings</guilabel>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_TitleBarM2</guimenuitem>: Middle pointer click on titlebar. Invokes a small
    menu which gives FvwmIdent, xwininfo, xprop, and two types of screenshot of
    the window.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_WindowOps</guimenuitem>: main menu of <emphasis>Window Operations</emphasis>
    invoked with a mouse
    click on left titlebar button. It has extended (<guimenuitem>More ...</guimenuitem>) and
    reduced (<guimenuitem>Less ...</guimenuitem>) version.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_WindowOpsMore</guimenuitem>: changes <guimenuitem>m_WindowOps</guimenuitem>
    from default reduced, to extended view (<guimenuitem>More ...</guimenuitem> option on
    Window Operation menu)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_WindowOpsRootWin</guimenuitem>: Standalone root window version of the Window
    Operations menu. Invoked with a click on the root window.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <guimenuitem>m_WindowOpsXterm</guimenuitem>: extensions for the
  <emphasis>Window Operations</emphasis> menu
    activated on (recognized) terminal application windows.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Mousebindings_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Mousebindings.conf</title>
<para>
 File <filename>NsCDE-Mousebindings.conf</filename> is done in similar manner as the
  <filename>NsCDE-Keybindings.conf</filename>. Can be overridden (.conf) or extended (.local)
  just like (almost) any NsCDE conf file.
  See fvwm(1) for "Mouse" commands. Here commands invoked with pointer
  are defined. As it is the case with key bindings, mouse actions are too far more in
  NsCDE than in original CDE. The syntax is described at the top of the file.
</para>
<para>
  Actions are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 1st (left) button left click: invokes Window Operations
    menu, double click closes (Delete) a window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 1st (left) button middle click: Move to Workspace menu
    double click closes (Close) a window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 1st (left) button right click: Move to Page menu
    double click closes (Destroy) a window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 2nd (right) button left click: Iconify Window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 2nd (right) button middle click: No Operation
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 2nd (right) button right click: Shade (Roll up/down) Window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 3rd (rightmost) button left click: (Un)Maximize Window 82%
    double click (un)maximizes 100%, covering Front Panel and it's area
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 3rd (rightmost) button middle click: (Un)Maximizes 82% and
    makes window sticky or unsticks it depending on window's initial
    state
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar 3rd (rightmost) button right click: (Un)Maximizes 82% and
    makes window raise or lower depending on window's initial state
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar left click: Moves window on move, raises/lowers on click
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar middle click: pops up menu with functions to take a
    screenshot of the window, identify with info (FvwmIdent), xprop(1),
    and xwininfo(1)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Titlebar right mouse button quickly raises or lowers a window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Pointer actions 4 and 5 (mouse wheel) are shading and unshading
    (rollup, rolldown) a window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Left pointer click on border or corner raises or lowers a window
    while move action will interactively resize the window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Middle pointer click on border or corner will only do lower/raise
    action, without resize on pointer movement
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Right pointer click on border or corner also does lower/raise
    action, but on pointer movement moves the window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Left pointer click in combination with control on border or corner
    calls a root window version of the Window Operations menu - this
    rare and border functionality is aimed for difficult situations
    where there is no other option easily available
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Middle pointer click in combination with control on border or corner
    refreshes the window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Right pointer click in combination with control on border or corner
    calls root applications menu (<guimenuitem>MenuFvwmRoot</guimenuitem>) - this rare and border
    functionality is aimed for difficult situations where there is no
    other option easily available
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Left pointer click on icon calls <guimenuitem>m_IconOps</guimenuitem> menu, while double click
    action deiconifies a window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Middle pointer click on icon calls <guimenuitem>m_IconM2</guimenuitem> menu
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Right pointer click on icon directly deiconifies a window
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Left click on the root window calls <guimenuitem>Window Options</guimenuitem> menu
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Middle click calls FVWM <function>WindowList</function> super-menu see fvwm(1) for
    <option>WindowList</option>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Right click calls main root menu <guimenuitem>MenuFvwmRoot</guimenuitem>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Pointer actions 4 and 5 (mouse wheel) will scroll between current
    up and down desk pages by 10%
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <keysym>Control+</keysym> middle mouse click will call extended version of the
    WindowList with additional window info such as page number and
    window geometry.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Pointer actions 4 and 5 (mouse wheel) will scroll between current
    up and down desk pages by 1% if <keysym>Shift</keysym> is simultaneously pressed
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Pointer actions 4 and 5 (mouse wheel) will scroll between current
    up and down desk pages by 1% if <keysym>Meta</keysym> (<keysym>mod4</keysym>) is simultaneously
    pressed, but in opposite direction then scroll with shift
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Left mouse button on border of the shaded Front Panel context will
    de-shade and reposition Front Panel
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Right mouse button on border of Front Panel will shade or de-shade
    Front Panel
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Pager-WspLocPager_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Pager-WspLocPager.conf</title>
<para>
Configures FvwmPager(1) type which is called from the Page Manager (PGM) or as
<guilabel>Local Pager</guilabel> from the right-click popup menu on Workspace Manager buttons.
This pager is transient and will disappear after being used with a pointer click.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Pager-GlobalPager_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Pager-GlobalPager.conf</title>
<para>
Similar, but bigger FvwmPager(1), invoked as <emphasis>Global Pager</emphasis> from right-click
popup menu on Workspace Manager buttons, or (by default) with <keysym>Meta+Escape</keysym> keybinding
this pager is transient and will disappear when used with a pointer click.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Pager-LocalPager_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Pager-LocalPager.conf</title>
<para>
Infostore variable <varname>pageraisefp</varname> in <filename>NsCDE.conf</filename> is by default 0.
If enabled, when active page changes, visual FvwmPager(1) will be shown in the center
of the screen near the top of it.
On <keysym>Ctrl+Compose</keysym> (<keysym>Ctrl+Menu</keysym>) and/or
<keysym>Shift+ISO_Level3_Shift</keysym> (Right Alt), pager will move to the position of
the pointer, it will eventually disappear from the screen after 1 second, 3 seconds,
5 seconds, 8 seconds, or 10 seconds if it looses the focus, or it can
be dismissed by pressing the same key combination once more while
pointer is above pager.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Script_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Script.conf</title>
<para>
Default for all FvwmScript(1) Module based applications and widgets. Script Path,
default font and colorset. All this values are defined outside of
this file, so nothing really should be changed here.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-WSM_conf">
<title>WSM.conf</title>
<para>
Non-FVWM config file. Here, names of the desks are provided and can be
changed manually of with Workspace Manager. Names of the desk pages
(for the menus) are defined here too, and manager manually only for now.
Option <option>WSPPG</option> can have value 0 or 1. If 1, small dynamic icon similar to
the Page Manager (PGM) will be shown right of the desk name on the Workspace
Manager active desk button, but only in 2 and 4 button configuration.
Off by default, edit manually.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Style_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Style.conf</title>
<para>
Main decoration configuration. <option>Style</option> '*' is applied globally. This is
the main source of CDE and Motif-like behavior. If user wants to preserve
CDE-like look and feel, this options should not be changed too much.
Otherwise, a plain FVWM configuration can be done which can drastically
differ from NsCDE, since FVWM has much more options and variants for a
huge number of tastes. <option>Style</option> '*' options are partially overridden or
extended in <filename>NsCDE.conf</filename> which can be generated with
<link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link>
or simply copied from <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/config</filename>
to <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> and edited to suit.
</para>
<para>
Options are grouped in 5 categories:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
   Default, or '*' styles
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Fvwm modules and FvwmScript(1) script specific
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Some basic sane defaults for common applications
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Menu styles (not a style commands, but styles anyway)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   Cursor styles (not a style commands, but styles anyway)
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
This styles can be extended and/or overridden by the user's own
<filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE-Style.local</filename>.
</para>
<para>
Colorsets and fonts used in this configuration are generated and stored
in <filename>NsCDE-Font-$DPIdpi.conf</filename> and <filename>NsCDE-Colorset.conf</filename>.
</para>
<para>
Man page fvwm(1) has a rich and extended description of what can be done
with a huge set of <option>Style</option> commands.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="Subpanels_actions">
<title>Subpanels.actions</title>
<para>
This file is not FVWM configuration file. It is written by the 
<link linkend="NsCDE-SubpanelMgr">Subpanels Manager</link>, 
<link linkend="NsCDE-SubpanelSettings">Subpanel Settings</link>, or
manually with editor, and read by the <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/generate_subpanels</command>
command which will generate
<link linkend="NsCDE-Subpanels_conf"><filename>NsCDE-Subpanels.conf</filename></link> file in user's
<varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>.
The syntax of this file is simple. It is CSV-like file where values are delimited with a comma ",".
Every line belongs to one of the ten subpanels. Comma and "'" characters cannot be part of
the field values. This values are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
   S&lt;X&gt;: where &lt;X&gt; is a number from 1 to 10 indicates which subpanel's line is this
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   NAME, WIDTH, ENABLED, ENTRY: second line indicates subpanel's display name, subpanel's width
   regarding font and long application names on the menu, state of enablement, and entries defined
   for this subpanel. ENTRY lines can be multiple (as much as screen resolution allows), other values
   must be unique for every subpanel.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   For NAME, WIDTH and ENABLED, there is only a third parameter: for a NAME the name of the subpanel,
   WIDTH is an integer (reasonable values: 120 - 260), and enabled is boolean 1 or 0.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   For ENTRY lines, there are fields application title, check type, icon path and name,
   and command with arguments fields that must be defined. Title is name of the entry. For example
   "Firefox" or "Workstation Info". Check type can be one of "FVWM-M" for FVWM module, "FVWM-F" for
   FVWM function, "OTHER" (currently unused), CHECK:&lt;appname&gt; where &lt;appname&gt; is the
   command which should be checked for existance instead of the first string of the command field,
   empty space (nothing between commas: <emphasis>,,</emphasis>), and NOCHK
   which indicates that no check for
   a command existance should be done in <filename>NsCDE-Subpanels.conf</filename>.
   Most of the entries will default to <emphasis>empty</emphasis> which will prepend
   <option>Test (x &lt;appname&gt;)</option> to the entry specification in the resulting
   FvwmButtons(8) config.
   Icon is full path of the icon file (32x32) which should belong
   to the application. and the rest of the line is application's calling command, possibly
   with options and arguments.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Subpanels_conf">
<title>NsCDE-Subpanels.conf</title>
<para>
This file is generated by the <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/generate_subpanels</command>.
It is static in system directory, but changable and easly generated in the <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>
It contains FvwmButtons(8) definitions of all 10 possible subpanels which can be popped up from the
<link linkend="NsCDE-FrontPanel">Front Panel</link>. There are 3 ways to regenerate this file:
<link linkend="NsCDE-SubpanelMgr">Subpanels Manager</link> tool called from
the <emphasis>Install Icon</emphasis>, <link linkend="NsCDE-SubpanelSettings">Subpanel Settings</link> tool
called from the titlebar popdown menu on every subpanel as <emphasis>Subpanel Settings</emphasis> or
manually by calling <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/generate_subpanels</command> which will
read user's or system <link linkend="Subpanels_actions"><filename>Subpanels.actions</filename></link> for
every subpanel and if it is defined in user's one, take this one while generating NsCDE-Subpanels.conf.
In system default, subpanels 2, 5 and 6 are disabled by default, but can be activated with a very quick
double middle pointer click on the empty launcher without arrow: a
<link linkend="NsCDE-SubpanelSettings">Subpanel Settings</link> application will appear on the screen
which has a checkbox <guilabel>"This Subpanel is Enabled"</guilabel> which will be checked out by
default, and can be checked in, and <guibutton>OK</guibutton> will enable subpanel with initial
system defaults for name, width and application entries.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-System-User-Tree-Layout">
<title>System and User NsCDE Tree Layout</title>
<para>
This section describes in detail what is stored where in NsCDE system-wide
installation hierarchy, and user's home directory <filename>.NsCDE</filename>
or <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>.
</para>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-System-Tree-Layout">
<title>System Tree Layout</title>
<para>
Everything from NsCDE is for now located as one compact place for easier
portability between Linux and Unix systems in
<filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE</filename>. Only symlink
to main starting wrapper <filename>/opt/NsCDE/bin/nscde</filename> is feasible to be put into
<filename class="directory">/usr/bin</filename> or <filename class="directory">/usr/local/bin,</filename>
since <filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE/bin</filename> doesn't really need tobe put in
user's <varname>$PATH</varname>.
</para>
<para>
This are subdirectories of <filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE</filename> with short
description what is what, and what is where:
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE</filename></para>
<para>
main top directory of NsCDE installation all further
descriptions will be written as relative to this directory
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<filename class="directory">bin</filename>
</para>
<para>
  nscde start wrapper called from <filename>.xsession</filename> or integrated as .desktop
  file in <filename class="directory">/usr/share/xsession</filename> is located here,
  as well as some helper
  scripts of the NsCDE which are suitable for general use. Front Panel
  <command>pclock</command> is also here. Pclock is the only binary part of the NsCDE
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   config
</para>
<para>
  Configuration directory. All .conf files described in documentation
  are here. They are read from <filename>config/NsCDE-Main.conf</filename> which is called
  from bin/nscde by fvwm binary with <option>-f</option> directly.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">lib/progbits</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Template X pixmap files used by <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> for producing
  user's copy in the <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/icons/NsCDE/</filename>
  this pixmaps are
  invalid as pictures in their source form since they contain internal
  macros for replacement with real colors. System starting theme is
  using their copied in <filename class="directory">share/icons/NsCDE</filename>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">lib/python</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Python libraries used by <command>themegen.py</command>: part of the integration suite
  for GTK and Qt.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">libexec</filename>
</para>
<para>
  The rest of the scripts (korn shell and python) are located here. In
  normal circumstances this scripts should not be run directly, but
  they are used by numerous NsCDE FvwmScript apps and FVWM functions
  as helpers and background program workers.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/backdrops</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Backdrop files. CDE and new, additional. Source for generation of active
  user's backdrop depending on theme, that is color scheme. They have
  <filename>.pm</filename> extension instead of <filename>.xpm</filename>.
  Bitmap files <filename>.bm</filename> (<filename>.xbm</filename>) are not
  supported by style managers and hence some of CDE's original
  backdrops of that type are in NsCDE converted to X pixmaps.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/cursors</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Custom cursors which are missing on plain X server installations but
  can be found in CDE. Referenced in <filename>config/NsCDE-Style.conf</filename>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/defaults/backer</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Default generated backdrops for first start (Broica, 8 colors)
  Referenced in system's <filename>config/NsCDE-Backdrops.conf</filename>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/defaults/pages</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Default page names for every possible combination supported by NsCDE
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/doc</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Documentation
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/doc/examples</filename>
</para>
<para>
Examples for X display manager and DE integrations, <command>sudo</command> for <command>shutdown
</command>  <command>reboot</command>, <command>pm-suspend</command> or <command>pm-hibernate</command>,
<command>Gkrellm</command> NsCDE skin.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/fontsets</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Default font sets used by the <link linkend="NsCDE-FontMgr">Font Style Manager</link>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/icons/CDE</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Original CDE icons
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/icons/NsCDE</filename>
</para>
<para>
  Custom NsCDE icons of which many are part of FvwmScript programs and
  applets
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/palettes</filename>
</para>
<para>
    CDE palettes plus a bunch of new custom palettes. Used by <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color
    Style Manager</link> and <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link>, as well as
    <command>libexec/themegen.py</command>, <command>libexec/backdropmgr</command>,
    <command>libexec/colormgr</command>,
    <command>libexec/nscde_palette_colorgen.p</command>y
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/photos</filename>
</para>
<para>
    A couple of nice free photos collected and resized for various
    screen resolutions. Can be used instead of backdrops (selectable
    from <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link>) or
    in <filename>$HOME/.xscreensaver</filename> for some
    screensavers which are loading photos.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/templates/app-defaults</filename>
</para>
<para>
    X resources for a particular X applications (like <command>XTerm</command>) which
    are processed by the <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> for user to be put into
    <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/app-defaults</filename> (if enabled).
    Referenced by the usual <varname>XAPPLRESDIR</varname> environment variable.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">share/templates/integration/gtk2_gtk3_qt</filename>
</para>
<para>
    Part of the CDE theme which are used by <command>libexec/themegen.p</command>y and
    the rest of lib/python/*.py to generate
    <filename class="directory">$HOME/.themes/NsCDE</filename> with
    a selected palette and color depth.
</para>
<para>
  share/templates also contains <filename>Xdefaults</filename> and some include files
    for it, as well as configuration for <command>stalonetray</command> if it is detected
    on initial setup, and <filename>BGdefault</filename>, which is a monochrome pixmap
    loaded as bare default early on start, before FvwmBacker(1) sets up
    backdrops on each user's desk.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">src</filename>
</para>
<para>
    Here is the patch for fvwm 2.6.7 and 2.6.8 which adds additional
    small features to fvwm, so we can achieve even more similarity
    between NsCDE and CDE. See <xref linkend="NsCDE-Patches-FVWM"/> for the details.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">src/pclock-0.13.1</filename>
</para>
<para>
    Latest version of pclock. Provided as C source (plus FreeBSD 12
    binary) for non-Linux systems and Linux distributions where default
    binary cannot work (no matter how small and modest dependencies it has)
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-User-Tree-Layout">
<title>User Tree Layout</title>
<para>
User's configuration is located in <filename class="directory">$HOME/.NSCDE</filename>
- this place is what is referred as <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> in this
documentation. There was no need to redefine this variable, since it server well for
NsCDE. If user has a plain FVWM configuration in <filename class="directory">$HOME/.fvwm</filename>
it will not be touched and can co-exist with NsCDE in that way. Here is the simple layout of things in
<varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>:
</para>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">app-defaults/</filename> directory:
   X resources referenced by the usual <varname>XAPPLRESDIR</varname> environment variable.
   Files inside are (will be) generated by the <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">backdrops/</filename> directory:
   If created, user can put custom backdrop sources here, and they can
   than be selected by the <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link>
   and processed with
   current or custom color scheme.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">photos/</filename> directory:
   User's photos which can be used instead of backdrops if selected in
   <link linkend="NsCDE-BackdropMgr">Backdrop Style Manager</link> or
   configured in <filename>NsCDE-Backdrops.conf</filename>
   manually.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">backer/</filename> directory:
   Generated backdrops referenced by Colorsets 31-38 for FvwmBacker
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">fontsets/</filename> directory:
   If created, user can put or generate with <link linkend="NsCDE-FontMgr">Font Style Manager</link> own
   fontsets here.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">icons/</filename> directory:
   Populated by dynamic menu action <command>libexec/nscde-fvwm-menu-desktop</command>.
   If directory does not exist, script will create it.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">icons/NsCDE/</filename> directory:
   NsCDE custom icons. Put here by <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> and the rest
   of the tools. Since icons from here are referenced with a relative
   path, whatever is missing here, will be loaded from system's
   <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/icons/NsCDE</filename> automatically.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">libexec/</filename> directory:
   If created, <filename>colormgr.local</filename> script can be written and put here, as
   well as <filename>fontmgr.local</filename> and other user's hooks.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
   <filename class="directory">palettes/</filename> directory:
   User can put custom palette files here, and they can
   than be selected by the <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> and processed for a
   preview or applied as new theme.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">templates/</filename> directory:
  Here, local subdirectory of <filename class="directory">app-defaults</filename>
  with tmpl files can be optionally created. Also, it is a good choice for Gkrellm or other
  files processed by the <filename>libexec/colormgr.local</filename>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename class="directory">tmp/</filename> directory:
  Place used by parts of the NsCDE and in particular NsCDE's
  FvwmScript programs for temporary generated files for previews,
  or as scratch and work directory. Tools are usually taking care
  to cleanup their garbage from tmp/ on exit.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>NsCDE-XYZ.conf</filename> files:
  Absolute overrides of <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/NsCDE-XYZ.conf</filename> files.
  If in existence, they will be read instead of system defaults.
  <emphasis>XYZ</emphasis> is here placeholder/example for Style, Functions, Keybindings,
  Init, Menus etc ...
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>NsCDE-XYZ.local</filename> files:
  Extensions, added values of <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/NsCDE-XYZ.conf</filename> files.
  If in existence, they will be read in right after their .conf main
  configurations from system (or local) directory. This is preferred
  way to extend functionality or override something not big enough
  for a complete "fork" of the config file. Colorset, Backdrops,
  Animate, Font-$DPIdpi, Init, and Subpanel are exception of this,
  that is, it is preferred (if not only thing possible) to have it as
  <emphasis>.conf</emphasis> files only and not <emphasis>.local</emphasis> files.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis>XYZ</emphasis> is here placeholder/example for Style, Functions, Keybindings,
  Init, Menus etc ...
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>NsCDE.conf</filename>: managed by
  <link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link>, Workspaces and Pages
  Manager, Pointer Style Manager and users own editor manually. See
  the rest of the documentation.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>WSM.conf</filename>: read/written by Workspace and Page Manager, WSM and
  user's favorite editor. Not an FVWM config file. System default
  of this file is <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/config/WSM.conf</filename>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>FrontPanel.actions</filename>: user's overrides/addons for Front Panel
    icons and actions. Written by editor, that is, manually only.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>GeoDB.ini</filename>: part of the Geometry Manager functionality. Written
    and read by the <command>bin/confset.py</command> and <command>bin/confget.py</command> on
    <guimenuitem>Save Geometry</guimenuitem>" and <guimenuitem>Reposition Window</guimenuitem>
    from Window Operations menu.
    Windows-like <emphasis>ini</emphasis> files are WAY nicer than dconf and such binary
    registry-like facilities.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>Xdefaults</filename>: Read on startup by xrdb(1).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>Xdefaults.local</filename>, <filename>Xdefaults.fontdefs</filename>,
  <filename>Xdefaults.mouse</filename>:
  Included with preprocessor directives from <filename>Xdefaults</filename>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <filename>Xset.conf</filename>:
  Configuration (a batch file or shell script basically) with
  xset(1) parameters for system beep, pointer, keyboard, and DPMS
  settings which are managed by their respective Style Managers.
  User can put here <command>setxkbmap</command>, <command>xgamma</command> and such additional X server
  configuration commands (or whatever one likes). Care must be
  taken not to mess lines beggining with <emphasis>#XYZMgr,xxxx</emphasis> till
  <emphasis>#end</emphasis>, since this is
  internal marker of FvwmScript's buggy <function>WriteToFile</function> function.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
 <filename>NsCDE-Sandbox.conf</filename>:
  If exists, used only in bare sandbox mode, where basic functionality
  of the NsCDE is needed, and not full DE-like environment.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Installation-Dependencies">
<title>Installation Dependencies</title>
<para>
For NsCDE to work, essential software is FVWM Window Manager. Almost
all is based on it. Since NsCDE is heavy user of <varname>infostore</varname> internal
variables and other new features of FVWM, development has been done on
FVWM versions 2.6.7 and 2.6.8. At this time, this are recommended, if not
mandatory versions of FVWM for NsCDE. Other dependencies, that is,
software used by NsCDE is:
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
Korn Shell 93. All shell script routines inside configuration, helper
  scripts and FvwmScript helpers are written with ksh. It is not sure if
  pdksh can be drop in replacement, but in tests on Arch Linux with mksh
  it became clear that mksh cannot replace Korn Shell. Korn Shell is available
  and it is free.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>Xorg utils</emphasis> (Fedora/CentOS RPM xorg-x11-utils) -
<command>xdpyinfo</command>, <command>xprop</command> ...
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Util <emphasis>xdotool</emphasis> - only if FVWM is not patched with WindowName patch for
the FvwmButtons
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>ImageMagick</emphasis> - really needed.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>Xscreensaver</emphasis> - optional, but
 Screen Style Manager will not work
 without it. Something needs to be installed for locking the screen.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>cpp</emphasis> - C preprocessor for <command>xrdb</command> functionality - for X
resources integration. Used by xrdb(1).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>xorg-x11-server-utils</emphasis> (CentOS, Fedora name) - xrdb, xset, xrefresh
mandatory for startup, some style managers and menus.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>python-yaml</emphasis> - needed for python part of the color theme management
and for Gtk+Qt integration.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>PyQt4</emphasis> or possibly python-qt4, or python2-qt4. This is unfortunate dependency
  which is further dependent on Qt libraries. NsCDE tries to have as
  less as possible dependencies, specially indirect (dependencies of
  dependent dependencies of dependencies ...). Gtk/Qt integration is
  borrowed from CDEtheme Motif/CDE theme project and adapted for use
  with FVWM (instead of heavy Xfce dependency) or standalone engine.
  In part of the <filename>Theme.py</filename> code, some png pixmaps are cut and colored
  with functions from this API. With present job and lack of time,
  there was no time to do this without PyQt4 for the first public release.
</para>
<para>
  On CentOS, Fedora, Ubuntu and probably Debian, also on FreeBSD,
  there should be no problem to install this with package manager,
  but in tests on Arch Linux, PyQt4 was obsoleted and user will have
  a hard time getting source from AUR and compiling huge bunch of Qt4
  libraries. There is possibility to replace PyQt4 with <emphasis>PyQt5</emphasis> imports
  in code and it will work, no matter that it will segfault and core
  dump on the exit.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>Gtk2, Gtk3, Qt4, Qt5, qtconfig-qt4, qt5ct, qt5-qtstyleplugins</emphasis>
  (optional) There is a great chance this libraries and some usefull
  programs using them are already installed on user's system. If Gtk and Qt integration is
  activated in <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>, there is no point not to have it
  installed.
</para>
<para>
  Notice about Qt4 and Qt5: <command>qt4-config</command>
  (or <command>qt-config</command>) and <command>qt5ct</command>:
  Although colors will be applied, for font setting to take effect,
  qtconfig-qt4 (or qtconfig) must be run, something changed back and
  forth, and then applied/saved - no matter that you will see fonts
  of your choice already selected. This can be considered a bug. Same
  goes for Qt5.
</para>
<para>
  Notice about Qt5: <varname>QT_QPA_PLATFORMTHEME</varname> environment variable must be
  set, and be set to <varname>qt5ct</varname> value in order to run <command>qt5ct</command> configurator.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Recommended fonts for as close as possible CDE look are <emphasis>DejaVu Serif</emphasis>
  for variable, and <emphasis>DejaVu Sans Mono</emphasis> for monospaced fonts. Check
  should be made if this fonts are installed on the system. For Solaris
  CDE look, <emphasis>Lucida Sans</emphasis> and monospaced
  <emphasis>Lucida Sans Typewriter</emphasis> should be installed,
  selected and used instead. (optional)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Open Motif 2 libraries for some programs, although it is not used in
any part of the NsCDE. (optional)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<command>Stalonetray</command> for "tray" facility (optional)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<command>xterm</command>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>python3</emphasis> (FVWM)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>python34-pyxdg</emphasis> or <command>python3-pyxdg</command> or ... (FVWM)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>libstroke</emphasis> (FVWM)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<emphasis>perl-File-MimeInfo</emphasis> (on some platforms and some fvwm packages)
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Installation">
<title>Installation</title>
<para>
When FVWM and all/most above mentioned dependencies are met, NsCDE can
be used. Present installation is very simple:
</para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
  $ su - || sudo -i
  # umask 0022
  # cd /tmp
  # tar xpzf /whatever/you/put/NsCDE-<version>.tar.gz
  # cp -rp NsCDE-<version>/NsCDE /opt
]]>
</programlisting>
<para>
  ... and optionally:
</para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
  # cd /usr/local/bin || cd /usr/bin
  ln -s /opt/NsCDE/bin/nscde
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
That's it. NsCDE is installed.
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="NsCDE-Startup">
<title>NsCDE Startup</title>
<para>
Session can be started from the <filename>$HOME/.xsession</filename> in last command line
as <command>exec nscde</command>, or <command>exec /opt/NsCDE/bin/nscde</command> or
<command>ssh-agent nscde</command> or with <command>gpg-agent</command>,
<command>lxsession</command> or whatever.
</para>
<para>
If supported by the X Display Manager which is in use, an xsession file
<filename>/opt/NsCDE/share/doc/examples/xsession-integration/nscde.desktop</filename>
can be put in <filename class="directory">/usr/share/xsessions</filename>
(or in whatever place your system and your X Display Manager reads this files)
and then selected from the manager's menu or similar selector. See the rest of the X Session
Manager integration examples are in directory
<filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE/share/doc/examples/</filename>
for MATE, KDE, LXDE and similar DE integrations and play with this if you
like.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Initial-Configuration">
<title>Initial Configuration</title>
<para>
Upon the first (successful) start, <filename class="directory">~/.NsCDE,</filename>
that is <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> is created, and only icons subdirectory
is created as <command>nscde-fvwm-menu-desktop</command> is run. User will be presented with a default
system setup and with default color theme <emphasis>Broica</emphasis> in 8 colors, and
<function>f_FindTerm</function> function will try hard to find some usable terminal
application and run it with setup. If Gkrellm, pnmixer and/or stalonetray programs are installed,
on the system and found, they will be run too.
</para>
<para>
Initial setup is a simple script (<command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/nscde_setup</command>) from
the terminal which will run automatically and will set up the following:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>X resources in <filename class="directory">~/.NsCDE</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Default background color (pre-FvwmBacker) from default theme</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Default <filename>~/.NsCDE/NsCDE.conf</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>New empty <filename>~/.NsCDE/GeoDB.ini</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para> <filename>~/.icons/default/index.theme</filename>
 (default X cursor scheme)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para> <filename>~/.gtkrc-2.0</filename> </para></listitem>
<listitem><para> <filename>~/.config/gtk-3.0/settings.ini</filename> </para></listitem>
<listitem><para> <filename>~/.themes/NsCDE</filename> </para></listitem>
<listitem><para> <filename>~/.config/Trolltech.conf</filename> </para></listitem>
<listitem><para> <filename>~/.config/qt5ct/qt5ct.conf</filename> </para></listitem>
<listitem><para> <filename>~/.stalonetrayrc</filename> </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Note that no file from the above list will be overwritten if it already
exists in it's place. It will be skipped, but GTK and Qt theme
integration files can be still written with <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>.
After <command>nscde_setup</command> script finishes setup,
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> will be run and
user asked to confirm default theme or change it. <emphasis>Do not</emphasis> avoid this
step, since some program bits are not fully setup on bare defaults,
(like a clock background) and must be
generated in the <filename class="directory">~/.NsCDE/icons/NsCDE</filename> directory.
</para>

<para>
After <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager's</link>
<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button is pressed, theme will be
regenerated. Gtk and Qt themes will be regenerated only if their
checkboxes in <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> are checked in.
Setup script after the finish will ask user to press <keysym>RETURN</keysym> to exit.
This is for user's convenience to read output of the setup for
informative and/or diagnostic reasons.
It is advised after this setup to open <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/NsCDE.conf</filename>
and set up InfoStoreAdd internal FVWM variables for <varname>terminal</varname>,
<varname>filemgr</varname> and <varname>xeditor</varname> to user's favorite programs for
functions.
</para>

<para>
Layout of the <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname> after the initial
setup should look like this:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>app-defaults/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>backdrops/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>palettes/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>fontsets/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>templates/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>photos/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>backer/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>GeoDB.ini</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>icons/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>icons/NsCDE/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NsCDE-Backdrops.conf</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NsCDE-Colorset.conf</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NsCDE.conf</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>tmp/</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Xdefaults</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Xdefaults.fontdefs</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Xdefaults.local</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Xdefaults.mouse</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
It is advised to logout and login from the X session after this,
and check if everything looks ok. Also, it is a good idea to start
using programs from the menu and examine environment around for a
half an hour or so, before running Style Manager (2nd button right
of the Workspace Manager on the Front Panel) to customize other
aspects of the interface. NsCDE is now ready for usage.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Integrations">
<title>Integration with X resources and widgets</title>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Integration-Xresources">
<title>Integration of X resources</title>
<para>
NsCDE is using it's own copies of <filename>Xdefaults</filename> and includes files for X
resources integration in <varname>$FVWM_USERDIR</varname>. X resources are filled with
this from <command>$NSCDE_ROOT/bin/nscde</command> main wrapper during startup as the
part of session assembling. Variable <varname>XAPPLRESDIR</varname> is also adjusted
to <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/app-defaults</filename>.
There can be problems while using certain X session managers or DE which are
clearing environment on a startup, and in this cases user must take care to put
environment from <command>nscde</command> wrapper in place after startup. Probably autostart job
in <filename class="directory">$HOME/.config/autostart</filename> and select from
Session Manager's app will do the job.
</para>
<para>
Special private paths for X resources are used in order not to mess
with user's maybe existing resources and files. If wanted, custom
app-defaults files can be places in
<filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/app-defaults</filename> or
even better, <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/templates/app-defaults</filename>
and reworked for <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> integration,
because if find in that directory,
and with <emphasis>.tmpl</emphasis> extension, it will be processed in the same way
as system files from <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/templates/app-defaults/</filename>
and put in <filename class="directory">$FVWM_USERDIR/app-defaults</filename>.
</para>
<para>
Plain custom X resources can be put in <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/Xdefaults.local</filename>.
This file will not be overwritten by Style Managers.
X resources integration is turned on by default in
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Integration-Gtk-Qt">
<title>Gtk2, Gtk3, Qt4 and Qt5</title>
<para>
<command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/themegen.py</command> with
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/lib/python</filename> and with
<filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/templates/integration/gtk2_gtk3_qt</filename>
are parts of the optional Gtk2, Gtk3, Qt4 and Qt5 integration suite. When run from the
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> or manually with the
<command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/themegen.py</command>,
with proper options, this will produce <filename class="directory">$HOME/.themes/NsCDE</filename>
directory with either or both Gtk2 and Gtk3 themes. <filename>$HOME/.gtkrc-2.0</filename> and
<filename>$HOME/.config/gtk-3.0/settings.ini</filename> will be edited to point to this
directory with <option>gtk-theme-name</option> option. Excessive button images on menus and
buttons will be turned off of course.
</para>
<para>
If Qt4 and/or Qt5 integration is also selected in
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>, files
<filename>$HOME/.config/Trolltech.conf</filename> and
<filename>$HOME/.config/qt5ct/qt5ct.conf</filename> will
be edited to use "GTK2" Qt theme engine. This means, there is no
Qt4 and/or Qt5 integration without at least Gtk2 integration because
Gtk2 theme in use is deciding what GTK2 Qt4 and Qt5 engine will display.
For Qt5 integration, make sure <emphasis>qt5-qtstyleplugins</emphasis> (or something like
that name) is installed: <filename>platformthemes/libqgtk2.so</filename> is needed.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="NsCDE-Integration-Custom">
<title>Custom application integration</title>
<para>
If <command>$FVWM_USERDIR/libexec/colormgr.local</command> exists,
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>
will run it if it's checkbox is selected. This script or program will
be run with a full path of CDE palette file followed by the number of
colors selected in interface (4 or 8). This can be useful for
regenerating settings of applications which do not use X resources,
and neither GTK nor Qt, but have support for some level of customization
of this resources. Also "skins" for programs like <command>smplayer,</command> <command>audacious</command>
and <command>Gkrellm</command> can be processed from custom <command>colormgr.local</command>.
</para>
<para>
In the directory <filename class="directory">$NSCDE_ROOT/share/doc/examples/Gkrellm</filename>
is the complete NsCDE theme for the Gkrellm.
File <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/share/doc/examples/colormgr.local.example</filename>
can be used for this integration. There are also examples for
<command>Stalonetray</command> and <command>mate-terminal</command>. Local script
<command>colormgr.local</command> will most likely use
<command>$NSCDE_ROOT/libexec/nscde_palette_colorgen.py</command> in some way.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Additional-Software">
<title>Additional recommended software</title>
<para>
Since NsCDE is basically a collection of configurations, themes and tools around FVWM
and not desktop environment in official definition, user must choose some favorite and
default applications such as X terminal emulator file manager, and X editor, which will
then be provided to him in occations where programs of that type must be called.
</para>
<para>
Apart from this, since <emphasis>system</emphasis> tray concept has been introduced on X11 and is
here to stay, user will need some standalone tray application. For this
purpose, a logical and really great <command>stalonetray</command> (Stand Alone Tray) is more than
adequate. If NsCDE example configuration for stalonetray is used, it
will have grid 3x3 and it's place will be in the bottom right corner of
the screen. Stalonetray is not integrated into Front Panel because it's
size cannot be known in all times: is it one button size, two, ten? It is growing and
shrinking depending on number of widgets or tray icons, and apart from
that, this can significantly alter the precious CDE look of the Front Panel. A window
with traditional mwm/dtwm borders and without title in corner of the screen is
default in NsCDE. Ideas are welcome.
</para>
<para>
X Terminal program? <command>Urxvt</command>, <command> xterm</command>,
<command>mate-terminal</command>, <command> terminus</command> ... user's choice
as always. As a slight recommendation, <command>mate-terminal</command> from MATE DE can be
set to look almost as Dtterm, but with richer menu and better UTF-8
handling, the bad thing is that configuration if not done via GUI or configuration file but is
stored in binary DCONF registry, and registry editor like <command>dconf-editor</command> or
or dconf <command>gsettings</command> must be used for non-interactive or CLI editing.
See the example in <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/share/doc/examples/colormgr.local.example</filename>
on how to integrate <command>mate-terminal</command> with a
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>.
Second (if not first) best choice is <command>Urxvt</command>, but since it does not have a menu nor a
real tabs, tmux(1), screen(1) or possibly tabbed(1) can be used for the same functionality.
Suggestions for more dtterm-like alternative are welcome.
</para>
<para>
File manager? Since author does not use them very much, there is no
some strong suggestion. Maybe <command>Krusader</command> from KDE is a best choice because
it has a lot of features and functions plus two pane mode for work. It
looks like a total contrast to GNOME way of doing things, so it must be
good, although it is not at all similar to CDE's original dtfile(1), but
dtfile(1) is a bad and poor file manager anyway. Another reasonable
choice can be <command>pcmanfm</command> or <command>pcmanfm-qt</command>.
For something more <emphasis>original</emphasis>, Xplore
file manager is written with Motif widget. It looks nice, but it is unfinished
(lacks real actions for many things, and instead input dialogs are
popped up for copy/paste ...) it is not maintained and developed, and
if someone does not brings it up from the past it can serve only for
overview of directories, simple actions and nice Motif decoration.
</para>
<para>
Editor? Gvim, Emacs, Xemacs, Nedit ... user's choice.
</para>
<para>
Another nice and useful app is <command>Gkrellm</command> for which
NsCDE has a ready drop-in theme called (of course) NsCDE in
<filename class="directory">share/doc/examples</filename> and it can be put in user's
<filename class="directory">~/.gkrellm2/themes</filename> and integrated with
<link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link>
with the <filename>$NSCDE_ROOT/share/doc/examples/colormgr.local.example</filename> which can be
installed as <filename>$FVWM_USERDIR/libexec/colormgr.local</filename>.
</para>
<para>
X Compositor: if user likes visual effects with tinting, transparency,
shadows, 3D, smooth changes and so on, <emphasis>compton(1)</emphasis> standalone compositor
is an excellent program and tool for such users - who want to combine retro and
modern style. Personally, I feel it like some kind of <emphasis>lag</emphasis>, no matter how
powerful GPU, CPU and RAM I have. I turn it on occasionally, more as an
amusement of xsnow, xsanta or xeyes type, but when I have serious work to do,
I simply turn it off in some moment.
Maybe it can be better if it is configured more conservative than example. See
<filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE/share/doc/examples/compton-integration</filename> for
a starting point.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Similar-Different">
<title>Similarities and differences in usage and look between CDE and NsCDE</title>
<para>
NsCDE is not a mere clone of CDE. Under the first visual impression,
there are unintentional and intentional differences.
</para>
<para>
First of all, it is not a standalone Window Manager or Desktop
Environment written in some language(s). It is a patchwork which
owns 80% of it's functionality to wonderful and powerful Window Manager
of FVWM. Other parts are configurations, scripts and programs which are making the whole
thing to function like the combination of the CDE experience and modern
powerful X Window Manager. Here are some things that I can recall to
be different - for the worse or for the better, user's opinion may vary.
</para>
<para>
What is similar or the same:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>There is a recognizable titlebar and buttons</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Titlebar buttons have the same basic (left click) actions as CDE</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Color themes and theming</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Front Panel and subpanels</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Workspace Manager</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Workspace Menu / Root Menu (right click on the root window)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Workspaces (desks)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Most of the icons reused</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Backdrops</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Style Manager launcher and most of the Style Managers</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Occupy Workspace dialog</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Workstation Info window (as found in Solaris CDE)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>FpLite (not with the same function)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Front Panel clock, calendar and check mail</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Icon positioning</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Look and feel via FVWM Styles</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Nice vintage but somewhat irritating wait cursor in the sand clock shape</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Various misc small imitations ...</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Differencies exist: for worse or better. They are described here in detail
with complete explanations:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
  Workspace Manager has a four fixed choices for workspaces (desks). As in CDE four is a
  default, but combinations with 2, 6 and 8 are possible. If reduced to
  2 desks, WSM buttons will grow in width to fill fixed space of the WSM
  FvwmScript applet. If 6 or 8 desks are configured, buttons will shrink
  and will be narrower. For that reason, in 6 and 8 desks mode it is not
  possible to have page indicator (<filename>WSM.conf</filename>: WSPPG) on the right side
  of the desk buttons,
  but this doesn't exist in CDE anyway, since CDE doesn't have concept
  of pages (in my best knowledge). This means that Front Panel has always a
  fixed width which is ok for a distinctive look and for screens with
  smaller resolutions - it will not grow or shrink depending of number
  of desks and their buttons shown in WSM.
</para></listitem>
 
<listitem><para>
  No drag and drop. This is specially visible in <emphasis>Install Icon</emphasis> action
  which actually calls custom tool Subpanel Manager for this actions.
  Subpanel Manager itself will be rewritten in a nicer and less buggy
  way on the first good occasion.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  No Dt Actions builder, and never will be. Write FvwmScript scripts
    or use some toolkit in combination with python, perl ...
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  No Application Manager. If integration with <emphasis>Install Icon</emphasis> and
    possibly menus will be possible with some file manager, it may be
    (re)invented in the future.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Keybindings are 90% custom made, and user have a choice to use it
    or - partially or totally rewrite it. There are more
    functions and actions in NsCDE than in CDE, and hence there are
    a lot of key bindings.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Mouse bindings - some actions like Workspace Menu in CDE are
    mimicked in NsCDE, titlebar and titlebar buttons too, but since
    there is no much of them in original CDE anyway, there is a plenty of
    custom mouse bindings and mouse bindings in combination with
    modifier keys. As for keybindings apply: use it or write your own.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> has numerous new functions: Gtk and Qt
    integration, X resources integration is optional, and it has even
    a possibility to run a custom script with required parameters of
    current palette and number of colors for external and marginal color
    scheme integrations - like <command>Gkrellm</command> for example.
    Palette color editor is missing. It should be possible to write it
    in the FvwmScript in some future version update.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <link linkend="NsCDE-FontMgr">Font Style Manager</link> is totally NsCDE oriented and doesn't work much
    as font management in CDE. NsCDE supports XFT fonts (disable
    antialiasing if you want <emphasis>extreme</emphasis> original look) and it combines 5
    groups of fonts in 3 sizes described in this documentation.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <link linkend="NsCDE-KeyboardMgr">Keyboard Style Manager</link> implements all options
    supported by the xset(1)
    on PC. CDE original in default installation at least, seems to have
    only auto-repeat and click volume controls.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <link linkend="NsCDE-PointerMgr">Mouse Style Manager</link> does not have
    configurable middle mouse (button
    2) action since this is not applicable very much on today's GUI widgets.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <link linkend="NsCDE-BeepMgr">Beep Style Manager</link> has a additional Beep
  button for testing during setup.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Screensaver Style Manager is in fact Xscreensaver setup. Perfect
  drop in replacement and much fancier than original.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <link linkend="NsCDE-WindowMgr">Window Style Manager</link>
  manages much more of window, icon, pages and animation
  behavior than original program in CDE, and even this is a small subset of
  options in FVWM. See it's documentation and fvwm(1) man page.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  <link linkend="NsCDE-PowerSaveMgr">Power Style Manager</link> is actually very
   rare in Style Manager across
   old CDE setups. It manages DPMS setting of the monitor with xset(1).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Startup Style Manager is available only if NsCDE is started under some X Session
  Manager. It detects supported DE's and starts appropriate settings
  tool for that desktop environment if it is found.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Pages: not present in CDE in best of my knowledge. Only workspaces (desks) in
  original. Page Manager (PGM) is a custom widget which is using place
  left bottom of the Workspace Manager. It can change current page
  or invoke ("...") graphical pager - FvwmPager(1) for a current workspace (desk).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Custom keyboard and mouse actions on titlebars, buttons and root window.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  WsPgMgr - Manage Workspaces and Pages. NsCDE invention.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  FpLite is measuring system load, not desktop activity. It has much
    more fine grained indication of activity with colors, and it's
    height is 3x of the original for a better visibility. On click it is
    calling FVWM function which will run terminal program with top or similar
    program, or anything else if use overrides that function in local configuration.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Calendar and Mail widgets are placeholders and simple indicators
  which are expected to be extended with already named functions
  to do what user wants.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
  Probably some more small differences.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Patches-FVWM">
<title>Patches for FVWM</title>
<para>
Optional but recommended patches for FVWM 2.6.7 and 2.6.8 are in
<filename class="directory">/opt/NsCDE/src</filename> directory.
</para>
<para>
This patches will add:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
   Three underlines Menu Style (used in <guimenuitem>MenuFvwmRoot</guimenuitem> for NsCDE)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   corrections for cursor icon under buttons of the FvwmScript(1)
    it is really not a nice thing to have <option>XC_hand2</option> which is usually
    used for hyperlinks as a pointer icon when mouse is above buttons. Planned
    to be implemented as an option, not to disturb old default, no
    matter how bad is probably that default
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   FvwmButtons(1) WindowName support - an native alternative to xdotool(1)
    workaround. It will set name and icon name of single subpanels, that
    is, every FvwmButtons object which has titlebar enabled with FVWM
    styles
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
   FvwmButtons triangle-in (sunken) support. Provides a 3rd argument
    for <option>indicator</option> parameter of the FvwmButtons(1) button. It can be
    "in" (default for NsCDE in <filename class="directory">config/NsCDE-FrontPanel.conf)</filename>
    or "out" to confirm the FVWM default. If omitted, "out" is default, since
    it was that way before this patch.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
In order to have patched fvwm, apply this patch or patches against FVWM
2.6.7 or 2.6.8 source and (re)compile FVWM. You can even make your own RPM
DEB, Arch, BSD, SunOS or similar package from that and install it.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Credits">
<title>Credits</title>
<para>
Apart from FVWM, GTK integration framework was forked from one
advanced theme, clock is old standalone widget which I have found
in the old X11 software archives while searching for something which
can act as a Front Panel clock. Pclock fits here perfectly. Xscreensaver
seems to me as a logical choice for screensaver facility.
</para>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 For forked CDEtheme: Jos van Riswick
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 For pclock on a Front Panel: Alexander Kourakos
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 For using Xscreensaver: Jamie Zawinski
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Missing-Parts">
<title>Missing parts and existing problems</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Application Manager: Maybe with the help of some extensible (but sane and standalone, with
titlebar) file manager, but question remains how to send enumerated apps
from such a file manager view to Front Panel subpanels or as submenu.
Probably external drag and drop applet which can be swallowed in
subpanels to accept drop with middle mouse move and edit subpanel
configuration? This will than replace Subpanels Manager app, but it
must also have functions for editing, deleting etc ...
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Action builder (dtaction) - not likely ever. Use FvwmScript or maybe some Python gui bindings.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Session Management (dtsession) - NsCDE can use the external custom
Session Managers from various DE's. See examples in
<filename class="directory">share/doc/examples</filename>.
Since there are similar programs in existence, plus FVWM's own functions for
automatic start of programs, NsCDE is more or less covered here.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="NsCDE-Ideas-Tasks">
<title>Ideas and Tasks for future improvements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 Some default editor to be used as a Application Manager
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Rewrite a bad Subpanel Manager and awkward subpanel handling
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Geometry manager: introduce step that will ask for Window to be
  saved in <filename>GeoDB.ini</filename> with Name, Icon Name, Class or Resource in
  order to be more flexible with applications which have multiple
  windows with the same class name.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Palette color editor in <link linkend="NsCDE-ColorMgr">Color Style Manager</link> is missing. It should
 be possible to write it in the FvwmScript(1).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Find or write the replacement for PyQt4/PyQt5 API in Gtk/Qt theme integration
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 FvwmScript for setting default X terminal emulator, X editor, file manager?
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Modern (in a sense of specs and completness) icon theme with the rest of
 available CDE icons (as much as possible)? Easy, but a lot of long time boring work.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 Localization. It will be hard and a lot of work. Specially FvwmScript(1)
 elements which are dependent on text length. Localization for Script
 elements, menus and documentation is the scope.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
 ...
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

</article>

